<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly merchant, or The great gaine A sermon preached at Paules Crosse. Octob. 17. 1613. By William Pemberton, Bachelour of Diuinity, and Minister of Gods Word at high Onger in Essex.</title>
            <author>Pemberton, William, d. 1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855988</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1213:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly merchant, or The great gaine A sermon preached at Paules Crosse. Octob. 17. 1613. By William Pemberton, Bachelour of Diuinity, and Minister of Gods Word at high Onger in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Pemberton, William, d. 1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Griffin for Samuel Macham, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bul-head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19569A on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GODLY MER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHANT, <hi>OR</hi> The great gaine. <hi>A Sermon preached at Paules-Croſſe.</hi> Octob. 17. 1613. <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM PEMBERTON, Bachelour of Diuinity, and Miniſter of Gods Word at high Onger in Eſſex.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. TIM. 4.7.8.</bibl>
               <p>Exerciſe thy ſelfe vnto godlineſſe. For bodily exerciſe profiteth little, but godlineſſe is profitable vnto all things, hauing the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edw. Griffin</hi> for <hi>Samuel Macham,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Signe of the Bul-head. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21501:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21501:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, and truely <hi>religious Lord,</hi> Robert, Lord Rich, Baron of <hi>Leeze, &amp;c.</hi> my ſingular good Lord, and Patrone, all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie increaſe in the great gaine of Godlineſſe, and godly contentment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr bleſſed day of Grace, (Right honourable Lord) in this bright ſun-ſhine of the Goſpell in this Land, as it affordeth vnto vs happie opportunitie, ſo it exacteth of vs ſtudious endeauour for prudent foreſight, and timely prouiſion of things moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull for our future vſe.<note place="margin">Luc. 19.42.</note> And <hi>oh that we would know, euen we, at leaſt, in this our</hi> long and faire Summers-<hi>day, the things which belong to our</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>peace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We fairely beare our ſelues and others in hand, that our <hi>Couenant</hi> with God <hi>of life and peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.5.</note> is firme and ſure, euen <hi>euerlaſting:</hi> becauſe the word of this couenant is ſtill remaining with vs,
<pb facs="tcp:21501:3"/>and that God <hi>will not turne away from vs to doe vs good:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 32.40.</note> becauſe the Lords goodnes is yet magnified toward vs. And ſurely the Lord will not be vnmindfull of his <hi>Couenant</hi> with vs, nor vnfaithfull in performance of his promiſe to vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.17.18.</note> if we ſtart not backe, and prooue vnfaithfull, but keepe <hi>couenant</hi> and promiſe with the Lord our God.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is with</hi> vs, <hi>while</hi> wee <hi>are with him: if</hi> wee <hi>ſeeke him, he will be found of</hi> vs: <hi>but if</hi> wee <hi>forſake him, he will forſake vs.</hi> Are our hearts then vpright toward the Lord? and is the feare of God (euen godlineſſe) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our hearts?<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.3.</note> If this be ſo, O happie wee, and euer bleſſed! <hi>for then ſhal our ſoule liue, and</hi> the Lord <hi>will make his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant euerlaſting with vs, euen the ſure mercies of Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True indeede (Gods name be prayſed) Chriſts true religion (the <hi>Doctrine of Godlineſſe</hi>) is by wholſome lawes of our moſt gracious Soueraigne, conſtant <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the</hi> true <hi>Faith,</hi> moſt firmely eſtabliſhed: by a good part of his Maieſties moſt loyall ſubiects ſincerely embraced:
<pb facs="tcp:21501:3"/>and generally approued or formally profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all, vnleſſe of thoſe vnhappie Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Nurſelings, who haue more deepely drunke of the <hi>golden cup</hi> of that <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh ſtrumpet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 17.4.5.</note> whoſe ſoule-killing poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth ſecretly ſpread to more dangerous infection, within the wombe of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining <hi>Mother;</hi> complaining (I ſay) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her life is in daily hazard by them, and yet ſhe can neither cure and heale them as her heart deſireth: nor yet be cured and eaſed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as her ſafetie would require. God graunt her mildnes toward them cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate not new dangers againſt herſelfe.</p>
            <p>Did the <hi>power</hi> and practiſe of <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in the reſt, attend the <hi>forme</hi> and ſhew thereof, then had ſhe not cauſe of ſo great complaint, but matter of ioy and good contentment, to ſee her children grow and proſper in <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> though this vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous broode lie ſtill crawling and gnawing within her bowels. But, alas! alas! our <hi>times are perilous,</hi> our eſtate dangerous:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.1.</note> the world is a gainer: God a looſer. And howſoeuer <hi>God hath graciouſly giuen all things that belong to life and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21501:4"/>yet is there but little increaſe, or embrace of <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> either in heart, or life. Many through blindnes are ſottiſhly ignorant of it, and cannot be brought to ſight of their miſerie without it. Many through ſecuritie are careleſſe of it, and will not be affected with any liking to it. Some through weakenes grow aſhamed of it, and are affraid to vndergoe any hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for it. Many through lewdneſſe are a ſhame vnto it, and by their inordinate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bemire and deface it. And it is well, if ſome through profaneſſe would not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and ſhame it, and by their graceleſſe impietie oppoſe againſt it. Many by an art of ſeeming haue painted their faces, but want the trueth and ſubſtance of being in the heart. Many through ſacietie grow weary of this <hi>Manna,</hi> and their full ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks begin to <hi>loath this honie-comb.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.6. Prou. 27.7.</note> And many hauing walked with God on earth, are daily taken hence to liue with Chriſt in heauen. Now while ſo many are ſeduced by the errour of the deuill: ſo many are enthralled by the luſts of the fleſh: ſo many are inſnared with the allurements of
<pb facs="tcp:21501:4"/>the world: and many of the beſt are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from earth to heauen: where doeth the ſound Chriſtian, and true godly man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare? or if he be ſeene, as (God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked he is) yet his life and courage is not ſuch, it may be feared, as once it was, or now ought to be. Oh, what ſhall become of Religion in this land, if our <hi>firſt loue</hi> to religion ſhal <hi>languiſh</hi> in vs?<note place="margin">Reu. 2. v. 4.</note> or what ſhall become of vs in this land,<note place="margin">verſe. 5.</note> if our <hi>Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke</hi> be once <hi>remoued</hi> from vs?<note place="margin">Iere. 9.1. Pſal. 119.136.</note> 
               <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines &amp; riuers</hi> of heart-bleeding <hi>teares</hi> ſuffice not to bewaile our ſinnes, which threaten our miſerie; nor to preuent our miſerie, deſerued by our ſinnes. The Lord in his great mercie graunt vs grace to know the time of <hi>our</hi> gracious <hi>viſitation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 19.44.</note> and to bethinke our ſelues of the things that belong to our peace, laſt hereafter <hi>they</hi> he hidden <hi>from our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that we could, in time, grow wiſe in heart, and rich in grace, and nouriſh the feare of God (euen godlineſſe) within our hearts! Then would the Lord <hi>ſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce ouer vs, to doe vs good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtill plant vs in this land with his whole
<pb facs="tcp:21501:5"/>heart, and with his whole ſoule.</hi> No power nor plot of wicked enemies ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt vs, if the God of power and wiſedome be loued and embraced of vs. <hi>The Lord will ſoone ſubdue our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.14.</note> 
               <hi>and turne his hand againſt our aduerſaries.</hi> No want of good or ſenſe of euill ſhall diſcontent vs, if this gaine of godlineſſe be fully poſſeſſed of vs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooueth all, from the higheſt to the loweſt to giue care to that godly exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that religious Ruler <hi>Ioſua, Feare the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ſerue him in ſinceritie, and in truth.</hi> Or if the fooliſh and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie multitude will not embrace ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed counſell; but <hi>it ſeeme euill to them to ſerue the Lord,</hi> yet muſt euery wiſe and couragious <hi>Ioſua</hi> put on this conſtant reſolution, <hi>as for me and my houſe, we will ſerue the Lord.</hi> What is that ſeruice of God in that holie reſolution of that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous Captaine, but the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of that <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> which ruled in the heart of that religious Ruler? What was the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but <hi>godly contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t;</hi> whereby he reſted wel-pleaſed in his ſound
<pb facs="tcp:21501:5"/>
               <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>eſtate</hi> now enioyed in this ſeruice of God? And what was the benefit he thence expected, but <hi>this great gaine of Godlines;</hi> euen fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>bleſſednes,</hi> in communion with the true <hi>God?</hi> This is that <hi>oyle</hi> (the <hi>oyle</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi>) which thoſe <hi>wiſe virgins prouided in the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of their hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25. v. 4.</note> and did furniſh their <hi>Lamps</hi> of their profeſsion therewithall. This cheered their hearts with ſweet <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment</hi> in their tedious expectation of the tarying bridegrome, and readily guided them to the <hi>wedding</hi> chamber, where they did enioy this <hi>great gaine of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the joyfull companie of their bleſſed bridegrome, in eternall ſocietie of felicitie and glory. Our profeſsion is the ſame with theirs: our practiſe alſo ſhould be the like. <hi>Let vs</hi> therefore <hi>hold faſt our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 4.14.</note> that outward <hi>profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>without wauering:</hi> but not a ſeeming ſemblance without the truth &amp; ſubſtance in the heart.<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>It is good that the heart</hi> which is naked to God, <hi>bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with grace,</hi> and that the life alſo which is open to men, be holie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable,
<pb facs="tcp:21501:6"/>
               <hi>as becommeth Saints.</hi> That the <hi>glorious excellencie of grace in the heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> being adorned with the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of golden profeſſion</hi> and practiſe of life, <hi>the kings daughter may be a fit ſpouſe for her bridegrome.</hi> God cannot approue of the truthleſſe ſhew of godlineſſe in our life, when the heart is not inwardly ſound and ſincere. Neither can we gaine ought by <hi>ſeeming rich</hi> in grace, when we are,<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.17.</note> indeede, both <hi>poore and miſerable.</hi> But if we ſhall ſincerely endeauour, that <hi>God may haue</hi> the poſſeſsion of <hi>our</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23.26.</note> and men the benefite of our religious liues, then ſhall God haue glory from vs, we comfort from God, and glory with him.</p>
            <p>And all this ſhall, by Gods grace, be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully effected, ſhall we finde and feele in heart and life the truth and efficacie of this ſhort ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <hi>Godlineſſe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is great gaine.</hi> Of which words I ſpake (as it pleaſed God to direct and inable me) in that ſolemne aſſemblie, whether I was, by authoritie, called to this ſeruice of God, and his Church: and where
<pb facs="tcp:21501:6"/>I endeauoured to become helpfull to my preſent Auditors, in their ſpirituall good eſtate, by labouring to perſwade them (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Title of <hi>Godly Merchants</hi>) to make ſure purchaſe to themſelues of <hi>this great gaine of godlineſſe:</hi> which as it is moſt comfortably attended of ſweete <hi>contentment,</hi> ſo it will aboundantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the poſſeſſor thereof, with all ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of moſt precious treaſures.</p>
            <p>What I then deliuered by ſpeach, I am now induced, at the earneſt intreatie of ſundry religious and wel affected, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit by writing to the publike view. The ground of their requeſt (as they well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me) and of my aſſent thereunto (as the Lord doeth witneſſe with me) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and hope of further benefite thereby, through Gods bleſsing, to redound to Gods people. If God in mercy graunt this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto it, I ſhall much ioy in fruition of my deſire, and end of my labour.</p>
            <p>I haue withall inſerted ſome things, which I had prouided to ſpeake, but did purpoſely omit, for want of time. As for the allegations of ſome Authors, now in
<pb facs="tcp:21501:7"/>the margent, as I did not iudge it fit, then to trouble the hearers with them; ſo may the readers at their pleaſure paſſe by them.</p>
            <p>Let my earneſt requeſt, to the chriſtian Reader, be this: that he will kindly accept, fauourably interpret, diligently peruſe, &amp; religiouſly vſe, this little helpe (a poore mite caſt into the Treaſury of the Church) to the furthering of his purchaſe of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> and nouriſhing of <hi>Contentment</hi> within his heart.</p>
            <p>And now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (Right honourable) I am bould to commend to the vſe of the godly Reader, theſe firſt fruits of my labours, vnder the Patronage of your Loe worthy name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Humbly beſeeching your Honour to accept of them, as a ſmall teſtimonie of that great thankfulnes, which, from my heart, I deſire to returne, firſt to God the gracious Author, and then to your Honour, as the ready inſtrument of a good bleſsing beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon me.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed your Hon. long ſince to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue well of me, and to reteine a purpoſe to do me good, &amp; vpon ſit occaſion offred, by moſt kind letters to teſtifie your pleaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:21501:7"/>yea, and earneſt deſire to become my <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone,</hi> and therein the happie meanes of my free and comfortable entrance into my Charge, and Miniſterie. For which ſweete bleſsing of God, my ſoule doeth daily bleſſe God: and it may well be vnto me a good encouragement vnto conſtant endeauour, in that holie buſineſſe, and waightie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, for the glory of God, the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his people, the comfort of my owne ſoule, and the better encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your Honour, in the conſtant proſecution of your religious and carefull courſe, of vpright diſcharge, of that great truſt, of a faithfull <hi>Dore-keeper</hi> in the houſe of God: that, as much as in you lyeth, Gods Church may be prouided of a ſupplie of learned and godly Paſtors, who by ſound doctrine and holie life, may promote the glory of God in the ſaluation of many ſoules, while they enrich them with this great gaine of godlineſſe, by faithfull diſpenſation of the treaſures of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The holie companie of theſe <hi>Godly Merchants,</hi> whereof this preſent Sermon doeth intreate, doeth greatly reioyce to
<pb facs="tcp:21501:8"/>reckon your Honour among the chiefe of their Societie. And it doeth hartily prayſe God, for his goodneſſe to you, in your large portion of temporall bleſsings, (as of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, honour, authoritie, and good estate) but eſpecially in Gods rich bountie to you in his <hi>ſpirituall talents</hi> (of ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the mysterie of godlineſſe, faith in Gods promiſes, zeale for Gods glory, loue to Gods Saints, Christian humilitie, and ſtudious indeauour to benefit the Church of God, with other precious graces of Gods ſanctifying ſpirit) thoſe moſt durable ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and inualuable treaſures of the beſt returne of <hi>Godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ioy of this happie <hi>Companie</hi> ſhall be much enlarged, to obſerue your wiſe employment of theſe goodly gifts of your perſon and estate, for your more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie growth in your heauenly wealth, for the greater increaſe of the ſweete <hi>Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of your heart, for the farther ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your holy profeſsion, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of your Lord and Maiſter, and aduancement of his glory, in the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his trueth, vnto ſtill ſucceeding
<pb facs="tcp:21501:8"/>times and perſons. And all this ſhall be happily effected, as by conſtant proſecution of all other your godly courſes, wherein the Lord expecteth your daily progreſſe: ſo in maintaining ſtill your deſerued Honour, of an vncorrupt <hi>Patrone,</hi> and crowning your good proceedings with conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance. That while too many enrich themſelues with the <hi>price of blood,</hi> your Honour may ſtill remaine in the bleſſed number of ſuch truely <hi>Honoured Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones,</hi> as (through faithfull diſcharge of that weightie truſt) purchaſe true wealth, and enriching treaſures, in furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the gaine of ſoules, both their owne, and others.</p>
            <p>The Lord, for his mercie, adde to this number of vncorrupt <hi>Patrones,</hi> make a daily ſupply of godly and learned <hi>Paſtors:</hi> bleſſe and multiply the companie of ſincere <hi>profeſſors,</hi> (theſe <hi>Godly Merchants</hi>) and glorifie his great name, in propagation of his <hi>Trueth,</hi> and enlarging of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>The Lord doe good in his good pleaſure to</hi> this our <hi>Zion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.18.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord build the walles of</hi> this our <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122.7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21501:9"/>Peace be within her walles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.7.</note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie within her pallaces.<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.5.</note> Let all that feare the Lord ſee the good of <hi>our</hi> Ieruſalem all the dayes of their life.<note place="margin">Nehe. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>And</hi> the Lord, <hi>in goodnes,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you herein, and wipe not out your kindneſſe which you haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the Houſe of your God, and for the Offices thereof. <hi>The Lord grant vnto your Honour long and comfortable life; make you thrice happie and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, in your perſon and posteritie; and giue you a bleſſed increaſe in this</hi> great gaine of Godlineſſe; <hi>that you may aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly finde much proſperitie in this life of Grace, and fruition of felicitie in that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all humble dutie in Chriſt euer bounden, <hi>William Pemberton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21501:9"/>
            <head>THE GODLY Merchant, or the <hi>great gaine.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. TIM. 6.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and beloued in the Lord;<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> The celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> which is aboue, &amp; the <hi>Mother</hi> of vs all, is the chiefe <hi>Citie</hi> of the liuing God our heauenly Father, wherein all our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brethren and fellow-ſeruants, after faithfull imployment of their ſpirituall <hi>talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.16, 17</note> hauing giuen vp to God a good account, doe reſt from their labours and their workes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. verſ.</hi> 21.23.</note> for they are entred alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into the ioy of their Lord, and enioy their deſired felicity in fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21501:10"/>
The <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt on <hi>Earth</hi> is likewiſe a <hi>City</hi> of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ. 2.19.</hi> Glorioſiſſima Ciuitas Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> yea a great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and a place of great <hi>Trafique</hi> and <hi>Marchandize:</hi> all the <hi>Citizens</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hauing receiued, from the Lord, their number of <hi>talents,</hi> are become <hi>Merchants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.15. &amp;c.</note> or traders, in one kinde or other, all vnweariable in their pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indeauour, and all ayming at one common end; their returne and increaſe in their profit and their gaine. Or if any be ſloathfull, hee hopes to purchaſe eaſe, and that, in his account, is a ſufficient gaine.</p>
            <p>Now as it fareth in other Cities, ſo it falles out in this; that all proue not wiſe and faithfull factors, vſing faire and honeſt dealing in their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and contenting themſelues with a good and lawfull aduantage: but ſome are craftie and deceitfull Merchants, who corrupt and adul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terate their moſt precious wares, and all to feed their couetous humour. Such were the falſe Apoſtles menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the former verſes: who
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21501:10"/>did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>teach otherwiſe</hi> then they ſhould,<note place="margin">Verſ. 3, 4, 5.</note> who <hi>conſenting not to wholſome words, euen the words of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according vnto godlineſſe,</hi> did ſet out religion vnto <hi>Sale,</hi> and vſed falſe impoſture for their priuate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: <hi>Suppoſing</hi> in opinion or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing in practiſe, <hi>that gaine was god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> While they meaſured Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity by earthly commoditie, and corrupted the truth of God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed the precious name of Pietie, onely to ſatisfie their greedy appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite: as though the myſterie of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> were a myſterie of <hi>iniquitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.16. 2. Theſſ. 2.7.</note> or a trade to ſerue to their ſordide and filthy lucre. And theſe are one ſort of Merchants who trade in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and theſe haue great doings and many partners, who make their faire profeſſion of pietie a ſleight to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their earthly gaine: yea and pretend religion the better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. Of ſuch falſe impoſtors, the Lord himſelfe complaines: That
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21501:11"/>
               <hi>their ſiluer is turned into droſſe, their wine is mingled with water,</hi> Eſa. 1.22. of ſuch our Apoſtle had experience that <hi>they did</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the word of God.</hi> 2. Cor. 2.17. and concerning ſuch he forewarnes <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus</hi> ſaying, from ſuch ſeparate or withdraw thy ſelfe verſe 5</p>
            <p>There is another ſort of <hi>Merchants</hi> that are wiſe and faithfull, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found the <hi>precious pearle</hi> of <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>pietie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.45.46.</note> preſerue it entire and vncorrupt without all impoſture or mixture of their owne. And ſuch a <hi>Merchant</hi> was holy Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15 10. 2. Cor. 11.23.25.26.</note> that <hi>Great</hi> trader both by ſea and land, who accounted all things <hi>droſſe</hi> and <hi>dung</hi> for <hi>Chriſt Ieſus alone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.7, 8.</note> the onely pearle of price, and did impart it to others in all fidelitie, (That they might partake with him in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wealth) while <hi>as of ſinceritie, as of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>in the ſight of God, ſo hee did preach in Chriſt.</hi> He accounted it great impietie to deale deceitfully, and extreame folly to ayme at earthly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21501:11"/>commoditie; and made this his rule of direction in all his trafique, which was an vnmoueable concluſion of his moſt ſerious deliberation: That, <hi>Godlineſſe with contentment is</hi> the <hi>great gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſcope of the words.</note>The intent of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Merchant (that I may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the allegorie) is to perſwade <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus,</hi> a much intruſted factor, and all others that trade in this kinde: not to follow the guize of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull dealers, as meaſured Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity by outward gaine (as though <hi>hee were the holier who is the wealthier</hi>) and made their preaching and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the doctrine of pietie, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a baſe and ſordide trade to compaſſe their earthly commoditie: but to become partners with him in his approued courſe: to embrace the Goſpell in all integritie, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues with their leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in their outward condition, ſo they were ſurely poſſeſſed of the <hi>rich pearle</hi> of <hi>pietie,</hi> able of it ſelfe to cauſe a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21501:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21501:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21501:13"/>
               <hi>wel-contenting ſufficiencie,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he backes this <hi>concluſion</hi> with all <hi>force</hi> of <hi>reaſon.</hi> That, <hi>Godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 7, 8, 9.10</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The contents of the words.</note>Theſe words then containe in them, a ſound <hi>poſition</hi> of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a true Apoſtle, oppoſed to a fond <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> of the falſe Apoſtles. Their fond ſuppoſition, in effect, was this. <hi>Gaine is godlineſſe.</hi> Goods are good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Where there is wealth enough there is religion enough. For they preached and profeſſed the religion of Chriſt, onely to purchaſe the wealth of the world.</p>
            <p>But Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſound <hi>poſition</hi> moſt acutely oppoſed to their fond <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> is this. <hi>Godlineſſe is gaine.</hi> True goodneſſe is the true goods. Where there is religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough, there is wealth enough. Yea, <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>great gain.</hi> Naked piety is the wealthy commodity. True grace is the richeſt treaſure. <hi>Godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine. Godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>attended</hi> with <hi>contentment.</hi> True pietie brings true
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21501:13"/>plenty, and of it ſelfe will cauſe a wel-contenting ſufficiency.</p>
            <p>The ſummary concluſion of all is this. It is moſt falſe, which the falſe Apoſtles did ſo profanely and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly ſuppoſe: that, <hi>gaine is godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> But it is moſt true, which the true Apoſtle did moſt fitly and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly oppoſe: that, <hi>godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.5.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thoſe are fooliſh and deceitfull <hi>Merchants,</hi> of ſicke braines, <hi>corrupt mindes,</hi> profane hearts, that <hi>ſuppoſe gaine to be godlineſſe;</hi> while they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh &amp; profeſſe the religion of Chriſt, for priuate reſpect of the pelfe of the world; But thoſe are wiſe and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealers, of wel-ſtaied heads, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mindes, vpright hearts, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme <hi>godlineſſe</hi> to be the <hi>true gaine,</hi> and as therewith right well enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, reſt well contented with a leſſer portion in their outward condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And further, thoſe are certaine looſers that account <hi>gaine godlineſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21501:14"/>for ſuch crafty Merchants as are ſo cunning to deceiue others, become ſo wilie that they beguile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſhall find themſelues but bankrupts, when they make vp their accounts, and are caſt into <hi>priſon</hi> till they haue paied their debts.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.3, 4.</note> In ſtead of an eſtate of plentie, which they vainely expected; they ſhall meete with an eſtate of miſery which they little feared. But thoſe are ſure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers who make <hi>godlineſſe</hi> their <hi>gaine.</hi> Who purchaſe to themſelues not ſo much this <hi>worldly</hi> wealth, as thoſe <hi>heauenly</hi> treaſures: who fill, not their <hi>houſes,</hi> but their <hi>hearts:</hi> not their <hi>cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,</hi> but their <hi>conſciences:</hi> who are rich, not ſo much in <hi>earth,</hi> as in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> not in <hi>themſelues,</hi> but in <hi>God,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> in whom are all treaſures of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> euen the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>God-head.</hi> Who became <hi>poore</hi> to make vs rich:<note place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note> and by his extreame outward penury, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our exceeding inward plentie. Who was poore for a time, that wee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21501:14"/>might bee rich for euer. Who will caſt vnto vs here, after our <hi>godlineſſe</hi> begunne, a wel-ſufficing competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and will repleniſh vs hereafter, when our <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is perfected, with al-ſufficient felicitie. So then: <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with contentment is great gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hetherto we haue beene taking a generall ſuruay of the coherence, and ſcope, and ſumme of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Now let vs enter into a more ſpeciall view thereof, as it is in it ſelfe an <hi>heauenly poſition,</hi> and a <hi>diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,</hi> ſhort but pithy, in very few wordes very greatly commending the worth and excellency of <hi>godlines,</hi> as the only <hi>pearle of price,</hi> worthy the <hi>purchaſe</hi> of the wiſeſt and richeſt <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this golden ſentence, or heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aphoriſme, wee may conſider a ſimple or naked aſſertion, <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>gaine.</hi> The parts of this aſſertion. 1. The ſubiect (or antecedent) <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> 2. The attribute (or conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent) <hi>gaine,</hi> are either amplifyed and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21501:15"/>illuſtrated by their ſeueral attendant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The attendant of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, true <hi>pietie</hi> is <hi>attended</hi> with an <hi>autarkie</hi> or <hi>wel-contenting ſufficiency.</hi> True <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> being (as I conceiue it) a <hi>fruit</hi> and <hi>effect,</hi> and (as I may ſo ſpeake) a <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe:</hi> borne of her, bred vp by her, &amp; an inſeparable attendant of her: and therefore they are by this particle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as with a golden chaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>godlineſſe</hi> (attended) <hi>with contentment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The attribute of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> that is, <hi>gaine,</hi> is amplified and enlarged by an attendant <hi>quantity, great. Godlineſſe</hi> with contentment is <hi>great</hi> gaine. And this attendant quantity, or <hi>greatneſſe</hi> imports a commendation of this <hi>gaine,</hi> which, the greater it is the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable. <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> is ſuch a <hi>gaine</hi> as is <hi>great.</hi> 1. <hi>Great</hi> in it ſelfe ſimply conſidered: as a rich treaſure of great ſufficiency. 2. And <hi>great</hi> compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely in reſpect of other gaine. <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21501:15"/>attended <hi>with contentment</hi> is <hi>of all the greateſt gaine.</hi> The <hi>true</hi> gaine, the <hi>great</hi> gaine, the <hi>greateſt</hi> gaine of all is: <hi>Godlineſſe attended with contentment.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen true pietie, which bringeth with it good contentment, or, a wel-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting ſufficiency.</p>
            <p>The particular branches of my fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture diſcourſe, (as by that which is ſpoken, you may diſcerne) for order and number may well be theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt concerning <hi>godlineſſe</hi> the ſubiect of this gaine.</p>
            <p>The ſecond concerning <hi>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the attendant of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>The third concerning <hi>gaine,</hi> the attribute of godlineſſe. And herein that.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. True <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>true gaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. True <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>great gaine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. True <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is the <hi>greateſt</hi> gaine of all.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And of theſe in order as God ſhall inable, and your patience, and time permit.</p>
            <p>The matter or ſubiect of this true,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21501:16"/>this great, this greateſt gain is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>godlineſſe</hi> or <hi>pietie.</hi> The name imports as much as <hi>true worſhip</hi> or <hi>religious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration.</hi> Which <hi>Nazianzene</hi> (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſometimes ſignifies worſhip of falſe gods) deſcribes to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Definit. 152.</note> The <hi>religious adoration of the bleſſed Trinity.</hi> The thing it ſelfe, which wee vnderſtand by the name of Godlineſſe, is of verie great and large extent. It conſiſteth of the concurrence of all thoſe precious gifts, and louely graces of the ſanctifying ſpirit of God: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth the <hi>whole</hi> body of thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine vertues of Chriſtian religion, expreſſed ſometime by the <hi>feare</hi> of God, as where it is ſayd of <hi>Cornelius</hi> that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a deuout or godly man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>and one who fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God.</hi> Where the <hi>feare</hi> of God, which ere-while notes out one <hi>ſpecial</hi> grace; or gracious diſpoſition, may well comprize, <hi>all</hi> religious deuotion &amp; due reſpect of God, both in heart
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21501:16"/>and life: and may plainly and brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be thus deſcribed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What' godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is.</note>
               <hi>Godlines</hi> is that religious reuerence &amp; awefull reſpect of God, which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true knowledge of God, and ſenſe of his loue, and cauſeth a ſtudious endeauour to walke with God, in all holie duties, both inward and outward, and that in ſincerity.</p>
            <p>This true godlineſſe (the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and cognizance of true-beleeuing Chriſtians, which diſtinguiſheth the new and right-born ſonnes of God, from the baſtard-brood of Satan, and corrupt generation of <hi>Adam</hi>) is for nature and propertie a <hi>religious reuerence</hi> and <hi>awefull reſpect of God,</hi> poſſeſſing the heart of man with all due regard of the holy preſence of God. The <hi>wel-ſpring</hi> or <hi>roote</hi> thereof is the feeling and effectuall <hi>knowledge of God,</hi> which is the ground of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, the ſeed of all vertue that groweth in the heart, and the firſt gift which God imparteth to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſelected to ſerue him, and to bee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21501:17"/>admitted into league and couenant with him.<note place="margin">Ier. 24.7.</note> Firſt <hi>God giues an heart to know him, that he is the Lord, and</hi> then, and not before, <hi>he will be their God, and they ſhall be his people.</hi> Without this ſacred and ſauing knowledge man is not <hi>godly</hi> but <hi>godleſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 2.12. Eph. 4.18.</note> not in <hi>Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with God, but a <hi>ſtranger from the life of God.</hi> Men cannot <hi>liue</hi> well that doe not <hi>beleeue</hi> well: nor <hi>beleeue</hi> well, that doe not <hi>know</hi> well.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Whence god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note>But from what <hi>knowledge</hi> of God doth <hi>godlineſſe</hi> ſpring? ſurely from <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>acknowledgement.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. Of the <hi>glorious maieſty</hi> and <hi>ſublimity</hi> of Gods diuine nature, and of his <hi>pure holineſſe</hi> infinitely ſurpaſſing the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of the moſt excellent creatures: in compariſon of whoſe brightneſſe the very ſunne is darke: in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whoſe puritie the very <hi>heauens</hi> are <hi>polluted:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 15.15.</note> for reſplendencie of whoſe glory the very <hi>Angels couer</hi> their <hi>faces:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 6.2.</note> before whoſe dreadfull preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the earth melteth,<note place="margin">Pſalme 97.5 Eſa. 51.6</note> 
               <hi>the heauens,</hi> flie away, the <hi>deuils tremble,</hi> and all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21501:17"/>creatures ſtand aſtoniſhed and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
               <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> ſpringeth from the <hi>knowledge</hi> of Gods <hi>al-ſeeing eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15.4. Hebr. 4.13.</note> al-knowing wiſdome, al-beholding preſence: whereby God pondereth the pathes, obſerues the geſtures, heareth the wordes,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſearcheth the hearts, tryeth the reines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15.11 Iob. 26.6.</note> and pryeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottome of <hi>hell and deſtruction</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
               <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> ſpringeth from the <hi>knowledge</hi> of Gods <hi>al-ruling prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.30.</note> al-commanding power, ſoueraigne authority, and vnlimited Lordſhip. Whereby God can, and will, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe and order all creatures and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, conditions and eſtates: and curbe, and keepe vnder al proude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſters and rebellious oppoſers; can <hi>bruiſe</hi> them in peeces with his <hi>iron rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.9.</note> and conſume them to nothing with the breath of his noſtrilles. Yea command and worke the weale or woe, life or death, felicity or miſery of all manner his creatures.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21501:18"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/>
               <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> ſpringeth from the <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of Gods <hi>exact iuſtice,</hi> and impartiall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: whereby the Lord,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.11.</note> not <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting perſons,</hi> nor taking rewards, doth diſtribute and diuide to euery one his deſerued right in good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, rewards or puniſhments, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience or breach of his holy, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and ſoueraigne reuealed good will and pleaſure. And all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations doe ſtrongly vrge and powerfully enforce vnto piety or godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> But that <hi>godlineſſe</hi> may indeed bee wrought, and grow, and flouriſh in the heart of a Chriſtian (and that hee may draw neere to God and not be deterred from God) hee muſt aboue al find and feele the quickening iuice of Gods eternall <hi>loue,</hi> iſſuing out of the roote of the true vine, <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> through conueiance and ſweete influence of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of God, which ariſing into the heart of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, will both mollifie, heate, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21501:18"/>effectually affect the heart, and moſt kindly cauſe therein true <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and religious reſpect of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nazianz.</note>And thus this true <hi>godlineſſe</hi> wrought in the heart being an <hi>habite of good</hi> things (as <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſpeakes) doth take the poſſeſſion and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of euery part of the ſoule, doth their reſide and rule and cauſeth an <hi>exerciſe</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and exerts and ſhewes it ſelfe in certaine actions and workes called the <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> or religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, both inward in the heart,<note place="margin">The large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and outward in the life, which expreſſe the nature and power of pietie. Of which kinde are theſe. Effectuall <hi>faith,</hi> diligent <hi>loue,</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>hope,</hi> reuerend <hi>feare,</hi> pure <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> ſound <hi>repentance,</hi> aſſured <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,</hi> all holy <hi>affections,</hi> diuine <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> godly <hi>reſolutions,</hi> earneſt <hi>peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> deuout <hi>geſtures</hi> vnſtained <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> religious <hi>ſpeach,</hi> vnblameable <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe actions of pietie doth our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21501:19"/>holy Apoſtle ayme, when he adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Timotheus</hi> to <hi>exerciſe himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to godlineſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.7.</note> When hee exhorts that <hi>prayers and ſupplications be made for all men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>for Kings and for all that are in authority, that wee may leade a quiet and a peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</hi> Laſtly, at this doth the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> leuel, vpon ſerious meditation of the finall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the world.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing the day of the Lord ſhall come as a thiefe in the night, in the which the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a great noyſe, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements ſhall melt with feruent heate, the earth alſo and the workes that are therein ſhall be burnt vp: ſeeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolued, what manner of perſons ought yee to be in all holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and godlineſſe,</hi> or <hi>duties</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe—being diligent</hi> in exerciſe of the <hi>offices</hi> of <hi>piety, that yee may be found of him in peace, without ſpot and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I take to be the ſum and ſubſtantiall nature of this <hi>godlineſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21501:19"/>which our holy Apoſtle commends vnto vs as the great gaine: to which if we ſhall adde one ſeaſoning grace, it will abide the touch, and bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sincerity a ſeaſoning grace.</note>This <hi>ſeaſoning grace</hi> is ſound <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the ſoule and inner man, freed and purged from diſſembling and hollow-hearted <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> ſo that it may abide the through tryall of Gods diſcerning view. And ſo much the name <hi>godlineſſe</hi> doth ſeeme to import, as taken from <hi>God:</hi> ſo that, in my apprehenſion, the <hi>godlineſſe</hi> of a Chriſtian is ſuch inward diſpoſition of heart, as conſorts with the nature and will of God: ſuch outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of life, as beſeemes the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God. Without this ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perfection of the inwards, and the heart, our pretended <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is little better then <hi>profaneneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> and our ſeeming pietie <hi>deteſtable</hi> hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.15.</note> But ſhall this ſound inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and true candor bee diſperſed as blood through euery veine of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21501:20"/>whole body of true piety, and as ſeaſoning <hi>ſalt</hi> bee ſprinkled on euery action and worke thereof:<note place="margin">Marke 9.50.</note> this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe ſhall be accepted for true and good: the heart ſhall be ſound, and actions approued: and then may this precious pearle of piety be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of God, and eſteemed of vs as our greateſt gaine, and trueſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>This (beloued in the Lord) euen this is the comely feature of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the ſubiect of our gaine, a thing of great worth and excellency euery way: which yet notwithſtanding is ſo ſmally reſpected, yea ſo greatly contemned, as is lamentable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, of the moſt and greateſt part, of this fooliſh world. Oh that our blind eyes were able to behold it! Oh that our peruerſe hearts were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to eſteeme it! Surely, ſurely: it would command both eye, &amp; hand, and heart, and all, to ſeeke it, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, to yeeld all kind and louing entertainment vnto it. I will not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21501:20"/>now ſpeake but pray. That the God of all grace would graunt vnto you all, this marrow of all grace, true godlineſſe and piety to guide both heart and life.</p>
            <p>Thus much I thought good to premiſe concerning godlineſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, which is preſuppoſed as the matter, and ſubiect of our gaine: now I proceed to the attendant of godlineſſe which is <hi>Contentment,</hi> for godlineſſe, is not alone but attended of contentment. Godlineſſe with <hi>Contentment</hi> is our great gaine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 2. gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall point of godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</note>The <hi>attendant</hi> of godlineſſe is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment:</hi> a moſt worthy wayting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide of ſo honourable a Miſtreſſe! True <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> is as it were a royall <hi>Queene</hi> full of Maieſty and beauty, ſtriking admiration, and reuerence into the hearts of all earneſt behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: and <hi>Contentment</hi> as a young <hi>Lady</hi> and <hi>Princeſſe,</hi> a pure and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Virgin of ſeemely feature and wel-pleaſing demeanure, euer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending godlineſſe as her Lady and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21501:21"/>Miſtreſſe. Both for progenie of the blood Royall, of of-ſpring diuine, drawing their line and linage from God himſelfe. For as <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is from God: ſo is <hi>Contentment</hi> from godlineſſe, borne of her, bred vp by her, and of bounden duty, an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>attendant</hi> of her; both are ſent, of God, into this world toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that being entertayned into the hearts of men, they might make both heart and life Godly, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: holy, and happy. And holy ſure and happy is that heart, that houſe, that towne, that city, that country, that court, that church, that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where <hi>godlineſſe</hi> and <hi>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> doe rule and beare the ſway. Theſe ſurely will cauſe an heauen on earth, and bring in time from earth to heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the word ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note>The word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] tranſlated <hi>contentment,</hi> ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds (as I may ſo ſpeak) <hi>ſelfe-ſufficiency:</hi> and points out ſuch an eſtate and condition, as hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of it ſelfe to furniſh it ſelfe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21501:21"/>withall; and needs not to ſeeke for ſupply elſe-where, and therefore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords <hi>contentment</hi> within it <hi>ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> ſuch properly and abſolutely is the eſtate of God alone, who alone is <hi>El-ſchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dai,</hi> the <hi>almighty</hi> and <hi>al-ſufficient God.</hi> God al-ſufficient in himſelfe, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and for himſelfe, and for all his creatures, of whom all creatures ſtand in need, but he in need of none, but reſteth, euer wel-contended within himſelfe as beeing <hi>Iehoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> the fountaine infinite and inexhauſt of his vncreated beeing, wel-being, life, wiſdome, will, power, felicity and glory, daily delighting and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing alwaies within himſelfe Prou. 8.30. and ſuch is the autarkie of the Nature diuine abounding in it ſelfe, not needing vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God, aſwell as godlineſſe.</note>Now as godlineſſe is from God, and goodneſſe from this firſt good: ſo is ſufficiencie and true content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from this al-ſufficiency of God (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) <hi>Our ſufficiency is from God.</hi> 2. Cor. 3.5. From God we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21501:22"/>deriue our beeing, our wel-beeing, our ability to doe well, to ſuffer ill: our godlineſſe, our goodneſſe, and our good contentment in our owne condition, which, with our godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wee receiue from our God. Which our holy Apoſtle moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly and emphatically expreſſeth to the magnifying of Gods bounty and our felicity. 2. Cor. 9.8. <hi>And God is able to make all grace abound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that yee alwaies hauing all ſufficiencie, in all things, may abound in euery good worke.</hi> As <hi>God</hi> is <hi>able,</hi> ſo is he <hi>willing,</hi> as in grace to beſtow god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: ſo with <hi>godlineſſe</hi> to giue this happy attendant of <hi>Contentment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By what meanes.</note> and that 1. While by faithfull promiſe hee endoweth godlineſſe with ſo rich a portion, as may wel ſuffice and giue contentment: for <hi>godlineſſe hath the promiſes of the life that now is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>and of that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. While hee cauſeth the godly minde recounting with it ſelfe it owne inward plenty (as beeing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21501:22"/>with treaſures of ſpirituall goodneſſe) to reſt wel-pleaſed, and wel-appayed, with what outward eſtate or condition can befall him: which, whatſoeuer it is, is that which his heauenly Father hath ſhared out vnto him, and therefore hee is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to reſt content therewith till it ſhall pleaſe God to better the ſame: hauing by the inſtruction of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe learned</hi> with <hi>Saint Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>in all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to be content,</hi> and if any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of diſcontent befall him, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires himſelfe into his counting-houſe: and there findeth himſelfe ſo well ſtored through <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> that hee ſees no place for <hi>diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is no ſtoicall ſenſleſnes.</note>Where note by the way, that this godly <hi>contentment</hi> whereof we ſpeak, is no careleſſe ſtupidity of ſtoïcall minded, or rather mindeleſſe and graceleſſe humoriſts, who are no way affected with any change: but as they neuer taſted of this godly ſufficiency: ſo reſt content in their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21501:23"/>inſenſible miſery. But this our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is ſuch as the heart affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſweetneſſe of Gods houſe can comfortably recount, and doth daily obſerue to iſſue from true pietie: which as it bringeth with it, <hi>wel-contenting ſufficiencie:</hi> ſo it poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the heart to holy equabilitie, and <hi>quieteth</hi> the minde in all <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">When con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note>Now the <hi>eſtates</hi> and <hi>times</hi> wherein <hi>contentment attendeth godlineſſe,</hi> are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally two. One in <hi>this life,</hi> the other in the <hi>life to come:</hi> in this of grace: in that other of glory. And as this and that life are not two in kind, but only one; and two in degree of grace and happineſſe: ſo is godlineſſe it ſelfe, and godly contentment, in theſe two ſeuerall times; not two in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but onely in degree: either ſuiting and conſorting with either condition, both liue and loue, goe and grow togither. When godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>beginnes,</hi> then <hi>beginnes</hi> content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as godlineſſe <hi>increaſeth,</hi> ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21501:23"/>is <hi>inlarged,</hi> and when god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is growen to <hi>full perfection,</hi> then ſhall the godly heart finde <hi>full contentation.</hi> Perfect holineſſe ſhall be attended with perfect happineſſe, perfect pietie with perfect felicity: and all this through full fruition of God in Chriſt, who is the wel-ſpring of our godlineſſe and goodneſſe: and the ful-flowing fountaine of our ſufficiency and contentment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Contentment attendeth godlineſſe in this life.</note>That godlineſſe in this life is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of contentment, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt out of the word of God: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally out of the Goſpell, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſtiles the <hi>truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.1. 1. Tim. 6.3.</note> or <hi>doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſſe,</hi> which holy doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine directeth vnto godlineſſe, and vnto godly contentment. Vnto <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> in this tenour:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke yee firſt the Kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe</hi>-purchaſe pietie, gaine godlineſſe. Then, <hi>exerciſe thy ſelfe vnto godlineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.7.</note> inure thy ſelfe vnto the practiſe of pietie. Vnto <hi>contentment</hi> in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Be not carefull for your life ſaying:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.25.31.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21501:24"/>
               <hi>what ſhall we eate? what ſhall we drinke? wherewith ſhall we be cloathed?</hi> (where prudent prouiſion is enioyned, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractiue care condemned) <hi>For your heauenly Father knoweth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> verſ. 32.</note> 
               <hi>that you haue need of theſe things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 33.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things ſhall be caſt vnto you,</hi> (beeing godly) without your vngodly care) <hi>let your conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation be without couetouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>and be content with thoſe things which you haue.</hi> And when piety prouokes to pray for more, it preſcribes godly mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, with this limitation; <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.11.</note> that is, a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable competency of neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion. But it condemneth <hi>couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> as the enemy of <hi>godlineſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.10. 1. Ioh. 2.15.16.</note> and permits not the King himſelfe to multiply his <hi>horſes,</hi> his <hi>ſiluer,</hi> or his <hi>gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deutr. 17.16.17.</note> aboue due meaſure of godly moderation: or in any meaſure ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing his <hi>diſcontent,</hi> or <hi>want of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God</hi> for a competent porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or needfull protection, by good and godly meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What ought to content.</note>Yea, beloued in the Lord, this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21501:24"/>doctrine of godlineſſe doth informe, what <hi>ought to content, viz.</hi> Meate drinke and apparell; if God giue no more. <hi>If we haue food &amp; rayment let vs therewith be content.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.8.</note> Nature (ſaith the Phyſician) is content with a little: as, <hi>not to thirſt, not to ſtarue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cibus &amp; potus ſunt diuitiae Chriſtianorum. Hieron. Bp.</note> and <hi>grace</hi> ought to <hi>content</hi> it ſelfe with <hi>leſſe.</hi> In this caſe, <hi>meate and drinke are the riches of Chriſtians:</hi> yea <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>water</hi> with the <hi>Goſpell</hi> are <hi>good cheere.</hi> More ought not to diſcontent, if God giue more. Leſſe if God giue not ſo much. (Any thing is more, then any man can chalenge. The ſmaleſt good is aboue mans greateſt deſert, all is of mercy nothing of merite.) <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> God meaſures out vnto vs, that ought to giue contentment to vs.</p>
            <p>And a <hi>godly</hi> man may <hi>wel content</hi> himſelfe in all eſtates: and if in any, hee finde himſelfe not well: it is <hi>not becauſe</hi> he might not therein be well: <hi>but becauſe</hi> hee doth not in ſuch holy manner demeane himſelfe,<note place="margin">Why a godly man is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note> as god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe would direct, for ſo out of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21501:25"/>queſtion hee ſhould bee well. True indeed it is, that contentment, which attendeth godlineſſe in this life, is not ſuch a ſettled compoſedneſſe of minde, and quiet tranquillity of all the affections, as neuer meeteth with any turbulency of paſſion, or is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer interrupted nor aſſayled of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contment. For as godlineſſe in this life is not perfected: ſo is the minde of a godly man not fully contented. But, through inward diſtemper and outward occurrence, is ſometimes ſhaken with vnſetledneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content. The ſea is not ſo calme in <hi>Summer,</hi> but is ſometimes troubled with ſome boyſterous winde: no not the ſtable <hi>mountaine</hi> ſo firme, but may bee moued with ſome fearefull earth-quake. So is it with the minde of a godly man: it is ſometimes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſometimes toſſed with windes and terrours. Yet ſo well is it <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily</hi> compoſed through habituall reſolution of dependance on God, and equability of affection in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21501:25"/>that it's neither ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſturbed, nor long diſquieted: but after ſome leſſer or ſhorter diſtemper, it doth quietly compoſe and ſettle it ſelfe againe, and through the power of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> doth recouer it ſelfe, and enioy againe this ſweete <hi>Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy, happy, yea thrice happy is that ſoule, that is ſo quietly ſetled, and ſo well compoſed, that it is not <hi>much</hi> ſhaken and toſſed with <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent!</hi> and ſo happy may euery one of our ſoules become, ſhall we ſeriouſly conſider,<note place="margin">How to come to godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</note> 
               <hi>how</hi> wee may become ſo happy. Which if any deſire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to know, let him lend his eare, yea his heart, a little, and caſt his eye of faith vpon the <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> and hee ſhall therein behold ſuch ſtrong foundations of true <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment</hi> layde, as that the gates of hell may well aſſaile, but ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Grounds of godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</note>The foundation of godly <hi>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath theſe foure <hi>degrees.</hi> 1. Gods
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21501:26"/>powerfull prouidence. 2. Gods pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent loue. 3. Gods gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. 4. The preſent portion which God beſtoweth vpon a godly man.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>ground</hi> of godly <hi>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is <hi>Gods powerfull prouidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> whereby hee wiſely ordereth, and ſweetly diſpoſeth all actions and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, conditions and eſtates. <hi>The Lord killeth and maketh aliue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe to the graue, and bringeth vp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord maketh poore, and maketh rich:</hi>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> 
               <hi>he bringeth low and exalteth: he rayſeth vp the poore out of the duſt, and liſteth vp the begger from the dunghill, to ſet them amongst Princes, and to make them inherite the throne of glory: for the pillars of the earth are the Lords, and hee hath ſet the world vpon them.</hi> The Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 147. v. 4. verſ. 8.</note> the Lord, guides and numbers the <hi>ſtarres</hi> in heauen, hangs the <hi>clouds</hi> in the firmament,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.26.28.</note> feeds the <hi>fowles</hi> of the ayre, clothes the <hi>flowers</hi> of the field, takes care for the <hi>oxen</hi> in the ſtall, multiplies the <hi>fiſhes</hi> in the ſea, numbers the <hi>ſands</hi> by the ſhoare,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21501:26"/>preſerues the <hi>haire</hi> on the head, and the drowing of a <hi>ſwine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.31, 32. Mat. 10.29, 30.</note> the falling of a <hi>ſparrow,</hi> the periſhing of an <hi>haire</hi> doth not eſcape the <hi>powerfull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of our moſt gracious God.<note place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> Yea and our God (in whom we mooue, liue, are) is able for <hi>bread</hi> to giue <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> from <hi>heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 16.14, 15. Exod. 16.13. Exod. 17.6. ver. 78. Exod. 13 21. Deut 29.5.</note> for <hi>fleſh</hi> to ſend <hi>quailes</hi> from the <hi>ſea,</hi> for <hi>drinke</hi> to giue <hi>water</hi> out of the flinty <hi>rocke,</hi> for <hi>ſhelter</hi> a <hi>cloude.</hi> For <hi>direction</hi> a pillar of <hi>fire,</hi> for want of <hi>new apparel</hi> can preſerue the <hi>old:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 3.15, 16 Exod. 14.21, 22.</note> for a <hi>paſſage</hi> can diuide <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and make a drie <hi>lane</hi> with watry walles through the deepe <hi>channel</hi> of the red <hi>ſea.</hi> Out of <hi>bondage</hi> can giue <hi>deliuerance;</hi> out of <hi>ſickneſſe, health;</hi> out of <hi>death, life;</hi> out of <hi>ſinne, good;</hi> and out of <hi>miſerie,</hi> can draw <hi>felicity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.23. Eſa. 50.2.</note> 
               <hi>His hand is not ſhortened that hee cannot now helpe:</hi> hee is now God <hi>al-ſufficient,</hi> as well as euer he was. And what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not our God doe for vs? <hi>God is able</hi> (ſaith our holy Apoſtle) <hi>to make all grace to abound toward you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that yee, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, hauing all ſufficiency, in all things,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21501:27"/>may abound to euery good worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery word hath it waight. Our God al-ſufficient hath al-ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for vs all, alwaies, in all things, to cauſe all grace to abound to vs, and to cauſe vs to abound to euery good worke. Oh the <hi>powerfull prouidence</hi> of our gracious God? Oh the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable foundation of godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment! What feare of want or woe can diſcontent vs, ſeeing our God hath al-ſufficient for vs? our God hath ſufficient wiſdome for our inſtruction; ſufficient power for our preſeruation: ſufficient grace for our infirmities: ſufficient plenty to ſupply our penurie: ſufficient mercy for all our miſeries: ſufficient comfort for all our maladies: ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient honour to wipe away our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy: ſufficient life to ouercome our death, and ſufficient glory to perfect our felicity. Thus is our God able to make all grace to abound toward vs, that wee alwaies hauing al-ſufficiencie in all things may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21501:27"/>to euery good worke. On this foundation may a godly man beginne to build his <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>godly contentment</hi> thus.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> The meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of Gods povverfull prouidence.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Doth any euill or croſſe befall mee? It comes not from the <hi>hapleſſe</hi> ſtroke of <hi>blinde Fortune,</hi> but from the <hi>al-ruling</hi> hand of an <hi>al-ſeeing God.</hi> Did the ſpitefull tongue of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy defame me? Or his powerfull hand oppreſſe and iniure mee? Or did any other creature bring any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill vpon me? Whatſoeuer was the meanes, or how ill ſoeuer affected to mee, Gods ouer-ruling prouidence hath ſome hand therein. Not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed himſelfe vniuſtly ſtriking, or inſtilling malice into the ſtriker, or exciting him to ſinne, or excuſing him in ſinne: yet guiding the blow, and directing it to me, as an actor in, not an idle ſpectator of the action: yet no author or approuer, but iudge and reuenger of the euill, of the action.<note place="margin">Ier. 25 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>Threatning &amp; puniſhing</hi> the inſtrument of the euill, and <hi>correcting</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21501:28"/>euill in mee, by the <hi>good</hi> euent of this <hi>euill</hi> accident, intended for <hi>euill,</hi> by euill man, againſt mee: but turned to <hi>good,</hi> by Gods goodneſſe, vnto mee. Well; whatſoeuer it is: Gods will appointed it, Gods prouidence ordereth it, his power ouer-ruleth it, his hand limiteth it: and, when he ſees fit, hee can as eaſily remooue it, as permit it, and turne this great euil to my greater good, and therefore <hi>I will be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ground of godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is Gods <hi>prudent loue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gods pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent loue.</note> Gods powerfull prouidence, able to worke our wel-fare, is ſeconded with his <hi>prudent loue,</hi> which makes him wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Such is <hi>Gods loue</hi> vnto a <hi>godly</hi> man, that he cannot but <hi>wiſh</hi> well to him, and <hi>doe</hi> well for him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your heauenly Father</hi> (ſaith our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.32.</note> our elder brother) <hi>knoweth that you haue neede of theſe things.</hi> God is your <hi>Father,</hi> if you be <hi>godly:</hi> yea, your <hi>heauenly</hi> Father; and beares vnto you the affection of a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21501:28"/>Father: and cannot but <hi>loue</hi> you, as being your <hi>Father:</hi> and that <hi>prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as your <hi>heauenly</hi> Father.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.11.</note> And <hi>if you beeing euill know how to giue good things vnto your children, how much more ſhall your Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, giue good things to you that aske him?</hi> God your Father is heauenly <hi>wiſe,</hi> and <hi>knowes</hi> better then you, what is beſt for you. The God of heauen is your good and louing Father, and will not, for his loue, ſuffer you to want what might doe you good. And therefore not to reſt content with that which your Father giues you, were either to make your ſelues <hi>wiſer</hi> then hee, as if you knew better then hee, what is <hi>beſt</hi> for you: or more <hi>louing</hi> to your ſelues, then your heauenly Father is to you, in wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more good to befall you, then your heauenly Father is, in <hi>loue,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beſtow vpon you. If you doubt of God your <hi>Fathers prudence,</hi> it is becauſe <hi>you</hi> are not <hi>wiſe:</hi> if of <hi>his loue</hi> to you, it is becauſe <hi>you loue</hi> not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21501:29"/>him. For God is not <hi>ineprudent</hi> in any of all his actions, nor wanting in <hi>loue</hi> to any of all his creatures: nor in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degree of <hi>loue,</hi> to thoſe that loue him well. And <hi>if God ſo cloathe the graſſe of the field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.30.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall hee not much more cloathe you? Oh yee of little fayth</hi> to your Father, if you beleeue not this word and promiſe of your <hi>Father!</hi> Oh yee of little <hi>loue</hi> to your <hi>Father,</hi> if you bee not ſo well perſwaded of your <hi>Father,</hi> that hee <hi>loues</hi> you well!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> The medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods prudent loue.</note>And this is the <hi>ſecond</hi> foundation of godly contentment: whereupon a godly man not doubting of the <hi>prudent loue</hi> of God his heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto him, muſt needes in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence content himſelfe with that portion which God his Father hath carued out vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſe</note>The third foundation of Godly <hi>contentment,</hi> (wherein Gods prudent loue moſt brightly ſhineth) is <hi>Gods gracious promiſe</hi> paſſed to a godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And what is this gracious promiſe?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21501:29"/>
               <hi>Hee hath ſaid. I will not leaue thee nor forſake thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.5. Hebr. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>therefore let your conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bee without</hi> (vngodly) <hi>couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bee content with ſuch things as yee haue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion</hi> But what if I haue not, but want, ſhall I then be content?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Feare not want, but feare the Lord:<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.9.</note> for <hi>there is no want to them that feare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obie.</hi> Yes, ſome that feare the Lord doe ſometime want (as <hi>Elijah. Lazarus. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 17. Luk. 16. 2 Cor. 1.8. Hebr. 10. Pſal. 34.10. Pſal. 84.11.</note> and many godly <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi>) Sol. <hi>The young Lions doe lacke and ſuffer hunger: but they that ſeeke the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing, <hi>good in it ſelfe,</hi> is <hi>not good</hi> for <hi>thee.</hi> If good for thee, it ſhall not bee wanting vnto thee. Surely <hi>the Lord will not faile his people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.14. Phil. 4.19.</note> Thy <hi>God will ſupply all thy neceſsities.</hi> Thou ſhalt ſometimes want indeede (as thoſe godly ones did) becauſe it is <hi>good</hi> for thee ſometimes to want. But thou ſhalt want nothing that is good for thee to haue: vnleſſe thou be <hi>wanting</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21501:30"/>to thy ſelfe. And <hi>therefore</hi> thou ſhalt not ſometimes want afflictions: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not <hi>good</hi> for thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71. Lam. 3.27.</note> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>to want them,</hi> but <hi>good to haue them.</hi> And when they are vpon thee, thou ſhalt not want due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in them, for God hath ſaid: <hi>I will not leaue thee nor forſake thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.5. Hebr. 13.5. Eſa. 43.2.</note> 
               <hi>I will bee with thee in the fire and in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The Lord will not forſake, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: but though hee cauſe griefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 3.31 32.</note> 
               <hi>yet will hee haue compaſsion, according to the multitude of his mercies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9</note> 
               <hi>His grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> Hee will <hi>lay no more</hi> vpon thee then he will <hi>make thee able to beare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> The medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</note>On this foundation may a godly man thus frame his ſanctuary of godly <hi>comtentment.</hi> God will lay no more vpon mee, then hee will make mee able to beare &amp;c. Either my croſſe ſhall bee moderated, or my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to beare increaſed. Either my burden ſhall be made lighter, or my faith ſtronger, as God doth preſſe me downe with one hand, ſo will he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21501:30"/>raiſe mee vp with the other. God can drawe mee to himſelfe, with the cordes of loue, vnder the roddes of men. And if my croſſes ſhall proue great, Gods loue therein ſhall proue as great. In greateſt croſſes God v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to wrappe vp the greateſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and turnes the deadly poyſon of afflictions into wholeſome and ſoueraigne medicines. That which in my apprehenſion may ſeeme the greateſt euill, Gods gracious diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ſhall turne to greateſt good. <hi>All things ſhall worke together for the good of the Godly</hi> (that loue God):<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> greateſt euils to greateſt good. The heauieſt croſſe ſhall finde the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt <hi>iſſue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>Death</hi> it ſelfe ſhall proue a <hi>rich reuenue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> bringing the happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of an eternall <hi>life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how ſweete a ſong of triumph may a godly man ſing, in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt threats or aſſaults of his moſt dreadfull foes!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A godly mans ſong of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</note>Whence my enemies intend mee greateſt <hi>daunger,</hi> thence ſhall I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21501:31"/>greateſt <hi>honour.</hi> My enemies may <hi>behead</hi> me, but cannot <hi>hurt</hi> me: <hi>Slay</hi> mee, but cannot <hi>conquer</hi> mee.<note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> we more then conquer.</note> My enemies may take away my <hi>life,</hi> but not my <hi>hope:</hi> My <hi>head,</hi> but not my <hi>crowne.</hi> Whether I bee woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or ſlaine, I ſhall not looſe the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> if I die in the battaile, I ſhall <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph</hi> after the fight, and if I fight till <hi>death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> I ſhall receiue a crowne of <hi>life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> I may goe (and if God ſee fit) I muſt goe, yea, I ſhall goe, by the <hi>croſſe,</hi> to a <hi>crowne:</hi> and through cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>martyredome</hi> vnto a glorious <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. A godly mans preſent portion.</note>What yet is wanting to a <hi>godly</hi> man, to make vp his bulwarke of <hi>godly contentment?</hi> Vnleſſe it bee the conſideration of his <hi>portion?</hi> Which yet is not wanting vnto him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath in part already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed it on him. And what is this <hi>portion?</hi> Surely ſuch as may well vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſupport his ſoule with godly contentment. Hee is already poſſeſſed df ſome part of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21501:31"/>ſelfe, which of it ſelfe is a <hi>goodly</hi> porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as beeing a rich treaſure of all precious pearles of grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Yea;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 57. Pſal. 16.5, 6</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my portion O Lord</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Dauid.</hi>) <hi>The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance, and of my cup: thou maintaineſt my lot. The lines are fallen vnto mee, in pleaſant places; I haue a goodly heritage. My fleſh and my heart faileth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.26.</note> 
               <hi>but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for euer. The Lord is my portion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.24.</note> ſaith the <hi>ſoule</hi> of mourneful <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10.16. &amp; 51.19.</note> in his dolefull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations. <hi>The Lord of hoſtes is the portion of</hi> Iacob: <hi>and Iſrael is the rodde of his inheritance.</hi> If the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe bee <hi>Aarons portion and his inheritance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 18.20</note> why ſhould not <hi>Aaron</hi> content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though hee haue <hi>no</hi> other <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among the people?</hi> And if the <hi>Lord</hi> bee the <hi>portion of Iacob,</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of euery <hi>godly</hi> man,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> who is of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God:</hi> why ſhould hee not reſt well <hi>contented,</hi> although hee want an inheritance in the things of this world? Oh happy man, that in that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21501:32"/>his want enioyeth more, then the world can either performe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> The medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mans por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The ſerious view of this goodly <hi>portion,</hi> of a godly man, may afford vnto him this holy meditation. God himſelfe is my <hi>portion,</hi> if I bee <hi>godly;</hi> and God al-ſufficient in himſelfe is al-ſufficient vnto mee.<note place="margin">Pſal. 100.3. Hoſ. 2.20. Ioh. 3.16.</note> God gaue <hi>mee</hi> to my <hi>ſelfe:</hi> God gaue <hi>himſelfe to me.</hi> God the <hi>Father</hi> gaue his <hi>Sonne</hi> to mee: God the Sonne gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to mee: God the Holy ghoſt gaue his <hi>ſeale,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.11.</note> to aſſure this gift vnto me, and ſhall I not be content? God the Father hath ſent the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of his Sonne into my heart,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> to make mee call God my Father, and Chriſt my Redeemer: and ſhall I not bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? <hi>That</hi> which I was,<note place="margin">Quod homo eſt, eſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus voluit, vt &amp; homo poſſit eſſe, quod Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus eſt. Cypr. de idol. vanitate.</note> Chriſt would bee, that I might bee that which Chriſt is: The Sonne of God by grace (as hee by nature) and fellow-heire with him, of all things, in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſhall I not bee content? What ſhall I ſay more? God the Sonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21501:32"/>all things from the Father for mee: that in him, and through him, and with him, I might receiue <hi>all things</hi> from the Father.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.21.22.</note> And why ſhould I not content my ſelfe with him; without whom all things are as nothing: and with whom no-can bee in ſtead of all things? Surely the man that is indeed godly, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly aboue all meaſure wealthy, and therefore <hi>I will be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell mee now (beloued in the Lord) can that true <hi>godly ſoule</hi> ſhrink downe through <hi>diſcontentment,</hi> that is ſo ſtrongly propt with theſe ſo many pillars? or can it euer languiſh, and waxe faint, while it doth ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recount and call to minde, Gods powerfull <hi>prouidence</hi> diſpoſing all things for him: Gods prudent <hi>loue</hi> intending all good vnto him: Gods gracious <hi>promiſe</hi> aſſuring him of his loue: and his plentifull <hi>portion,</hi> as a pawne of Gods gracious promiſe? While hee hath receiued godlineſſe, as a treaſure of goodneſſe, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21501:33"/>as a pledge of his happineſſe, and ſome meaſure of grace as a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of vnmeaſurable glory? The <hi>raine</hi> of afflictions may <hi>fall</hi> indeed:<note place="margin">Mat. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>floods</hi> of perſecution may <hi>come,</hi> the <hi>windes</hi> of temptations may <hi>blow,</hi> and <hi>beate vpon the houſe of</hi> a godly mans <hi>contentment:</hi> and ſhake and batter it, but it ſhall not fall: for it is builded on the foundations of God. Euen vpon the rocke Chriſt Ieſus, and <hi>chiefe corner ſtone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.6. &amp; verſ. 5.</note> vpon whom all godly men as <hi>liuing ſtones</hi> are built, and whereupon alſo they build and found their impregnable fortreſſe of <hi>godly contentment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On theſe grounds and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doth a godly man, when hee is himſelfe, build a ſanctuary to his ſoule of godly contentment: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee doth <hi>ſhelter,</hi> and ſolace him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in all the changes of this preſent mortality, in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe of the foure grounds of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>If God, in goodneſſe, giue aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, hee is ioyfull, and receiues it thankefully: if a competency, hee is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21501:33"/>cheerefull, and enioyes it comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably: if but a little, he is quieted, and accepts it willingly: if not any thing at all, yet hee is patient, and waiteth hopefully. For hee wiſely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; that God giues aboundantly, that man might bee an inſtrument of Gods bounty. God giues mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, that hee might not bee cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with ſuperfluity. God giues ſparingly, that hee might aske both theſe, and <hi>better</hi> things, more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Yea, God ſomtimes with-holds theſe outward things, and ſendeth croſſes in ſtead of them: for tryall of ſome grace, exerciſe of ſome vertue, preuention of ſome daunger, cure of ſome diſeaſe. To weane him from the world, to direct him toward heauen: to draw him to himſelfe: or ſome way, or other, for Gods glory, others example, and his owne true good. He knowes that Gods <hi>proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> diſpoſeth of all: Gods <hi>loue</hi> to him is firme in all:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> Gods <hi>promiſe</hi> is paſſed, that all ſhall turne to his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21501:34"/>good: and his preſent <hi>portion</hi> is not only good, but a pawne of a greater. If more were now behoouefull, hee ſhould not want it: and ſeeing more is not giuen, he feeles no want with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. But finds a ſupply in his ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> which is euer attended of wel-pleaſing <hi>Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What now is there, in al the world, that can threaten, and cauſe diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment vnto a godly man? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many things threaten it:<note place="margin">4. Cauſes of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> as namely theſe foure. Firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and remembrance of <hi>euill committed.</hi> Secondly, ſtrength and violence of <hi>temptation</hi> enforced. Thirdly, ſenſe, or feare of <hi>euill ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</hi> Fourthly, want and defect of <hi>good</hi> deſired. And theſe indeed, are of great force to worke or threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten diſcontentment. For where guilt of ſinne is not remooued: where aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and temptations are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled: where the bitterneſſe of croſſes is not ſweetened: and where
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21501:34"/>deſire of good is not competently ſupplied, peace and contentment cannot lodge in the heart of any mortall man. Here is a large field opened, but I may not walke therein at length. In one word therefore. God be thanked.<note place="margin">Theſe cauſes remoued.</note> 1. Chriſt hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and the guilt of ſinne is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. 2. Chriſt hath conquered, and <hi>temptation</hi> ſhall bee vanquiſhed. 3. The comforter is ſent, and <hi>croſſes</hi> are ſweetned. 4. Heauen is prepared, and all <hi>wants</hi> ſhall bee ſupplied, vnto a godly man, and therefore a godly man may well content himſelfe to liue by faith for the time of this life, and to comfort himſelfe by aſſured expectation of ioyfull fruition of all deſired good, and ſafe exemption from all ſuſpected euill.<note place="margin">Of theſe more largely.</note> More large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cauſe of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> and remembrance of <hi>ſinne committed,</hi> is of great force to diſeaſe the minde, and to diſtemper the heart with diſcontentment. For howſoeuer <hi>ſinne</hi> proffer delight, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21501:35"/>promiſe contentment, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: yet it worketh woe, and breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſorrow, in the ending, and neuer can true contentment lodge in the heart within, as long as the guilt of ſinne is not remooued out. Sinne cauſeth God to bee diſcontent with man, man with himſelfe, while God, &amp; his conſcience do war againſt him, what can worke contentment in him?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued.</note>But God bee thanked, Chriſt hath ſuffered, and Gods iuſtice is ſatisfied, ſinne remitted, God reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a godly man, by his faith in Chriſt his perſon is iuſtified, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence pacified, affections quieted, <hi>diſcontentment</hi> remooued, and his heart is refreſhed with new delight, in the renouation of his couenant of peace betweene his late offended, but now wel-pleaſed Father, and his late diſquieted, but now appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſcience; which formerly was an accuſer and cauſed bitter ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but now is become an excuſer
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21501:35"/>and cauſeth ſweete reioycing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Cauſe of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>As <hi>ſinnes</hi> committed cauſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment: ſo importunate aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of <hi>new temptations</hi> worke much diſturbance; and neuer ceaſe to vexe and diſquiet, till they be either vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanquiſhed, or ſtrongly repelled. The ſoule is not contented, vntill it bee ſetled; neuer ſetled, while it is importunately moleſted: and as this moleſtation cannot bee auoided: ſo danger of falling cannot, by nature, bee preuented.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued.</note>But herein a Chriſtian hath ſuch a priuiledge as can exempt him from the <hi>greateſt</hi> daunger of that euill which Satan enforceth, and nature furthereth. For the doctrine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe doth ſufficiently informe him, and the power of godlineſſe doth in ſome meaſure inable him, to compoſe diſordered paſſion within, &amp; to reſiſt diſturbing aſſaults with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. The religious exerciſe of <hi>mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> doth expell the venome of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous corruptions, and the skilfull
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21501:36"/>vſe of the ſhield of <hi>faith</hi> doth repell the poyſoned darts of temptations. Or if they preſſe ſo ſore vpon him that he cannot ouer-maſter them, yet doth hee ſo quell and weaken them, that they cannot conquerre him. He knowes that if he fight manfully, hee ſhall winne the field; and though he be pricked and wounded, yet he ſhal not bee <hi>killed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grauiter ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, minime ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ratus. Aug. de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it. Dei. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Hee finds his heart religiouſly diſpoſed to pleaſe the Lord, and abſolutely reſolued, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide, to his power, the offence of God, and cries for helpe when hee feeles the danger, and ſo rides at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in moſt boiſterous ſtormes, feeles ground of comfort in greateſt depthes, and holds vnſurpriſed, in moſt violent aſſaults, his impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fortreſſe of godly <hi>Contentment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Cauſe of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               <hi>Croſſes</hi> doe naturally diſquiet the minde, which, when it is croſſed, groweth diſcontented. Now the life of a Chriſtian lies expoſed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and croſſe followes croſſe, as waue after waue. The latter of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21501:36"/>ouer-takes the former, and ſometimes many doe meete togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as diſeaſe of body, loſſe of goods, defamation in name, diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of hopes, or other ſad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents) which preſſing ſore on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, driue oft to great exigence and dangerous extremities, and theſe make a naturall man weary of his part, yea of his life, and ſo diſtract him, that hee is ſcarce himſelfe; but ſometimes breakes out into gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous complaints, and opens his mouth againſt the God of heauen; or, in miſerable ſilence, makes his own hands the Chirurgeons by deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate cruelty to ſeeke for hopeleſſe remedie, or, if hee ſuffer himſelfe to liue, hee liues diſquieted, and ſo his minde is diſcontented, and a man truely godly, through violence of the aſſault, and weakeneſſe of grace, may be drawen very farre this way, and no humane skill can inuent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, to cure ſuch biting and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maladies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21501:37"/>
               <note place="margin">3. Cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued.</note>But <hi>godlineſſe</hi> in this point of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt extremity is of ſoue aigne force and experienced vertue, both to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vnneceſſary croſſes, which god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men draw downe vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; and to mitigate and allay the force of ſuch, as men vſe to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate againſt themſelues; and ſafely to bring through ſuch bottomleſſe depthes, as wherein the vngodly are vtterly ouerwhelmed. And when imaginary croſſes, to a godleſſe man, ſeeme heauy and vnſupportable: the trueſt preſſures, to a godly man, grow eaſie &amp; comfortable; through the worke and operation of the <hi>ſpirit of comfort.</hi> Hence, for the moſt part, it comes to paſſe;<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.</note> that, after ſome conflicts and firſt aſſaults, a godlie wiſe and couragious Chriſtian doth take to himſelfe ſuch heart of grace, (while the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of grace doth poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the heart) that hee declines the dint of the moſt deadly blowes. Godlineſſe doth inſtruct, both cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely to expect them, wiſely to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21501:37"/>foreſee them, timely to prouide for them, reſolutely to vndertake them, patiently to beare them, conſtantly to paſſe through them, and prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make aduantage of them. And not onely to bee cheerefull in them, but thankefull for them; as true to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods Fatherly loue, needfull promoters of ſanctification, and preſent pawnes of future good: of a crowne of <hi>glory,</hi> after a penny-weight of the <hi>Croſſe;</hi> and <hi>eternity</hi> of ioy,<note place="margin">2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>momentanie</hi> ſufferings. And this is that which enlarged the hearts of the faithfull to ioy and exultation in the <hi>fornace</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3. Dan. 6. Act. 16.</note> in the <hi>denne</hi> of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in the <hi>ſtockes,</hi> at the ſtake, in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in death: and is the <hi>quiet fruite of righteouſneſſe to all that are exerciſed thereby.</hi> So that hee hath but ſmall experience of the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who hath not learned ſome meaſure of contentment in preſent miſeries, on aſſured expectation of future <hi>deliuerance,</hi> and infallible hope of a <hi>better reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 34.19. Hebr. 11.35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21501:38"/>
               <note place="margin">4 Cauſe of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Laſtly, the preſent <hi>want of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired good</hi> doth greatly vnſettle and diſcontent the minde, for <hi>hope defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is the languiſhing of the ſoule.</hi> It is the nature of the deſire, ſtill to put forth it ſelfe, vntill it receiue wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſatiſfaction, through fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome deſired good. Now were the deſire directed by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and bounded within the limits of Chriſtian moderation, it were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to ſatisfie and well to content it. But as it is euer ranging and roauing after euery faire-ſeeming ſhew, ſo it is not alwaies ſatisfied with ſound and ſolid good; and while it care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly neglecteth the true good, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines vnprouided of true content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued by two meanes.</note>But <hi>godlineſſe</hi> will prouide for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the deſires vpon due conſideration of thoſe fore-named grounds. And whereas good things deſired are either earthly, or heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it teacheth moderation toward thoſe, giues direction to theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21501:38"/>
               <note place="margin">1. Moderation of deſire of earthly things.</note>1. It teacheth to <hi>moderate</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of earthly things; to accuſtome himſelfe to liue of a little, and to bee content: and as for ſuperfluities, not to affect it, in heaping together theſe earthly things; as vnworthy for themſelues to bee deſired or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: the inordinate deſire whereof, either depriueth of poſſeſſion of them, or diſpoſſeſſeth of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them. So that hee that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth them more then hee ſhould, doth either looſe them ſooner then he would, or not finde that content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them which hee expecteth, while he makes a God of them, and God an Idol, and more then this; godlineſſe teacheth moderation in care for them (which followes vpon and draweth after it, deſire of them) by calling to minde thoſe heauenly exhortations. <hi>In nothing bee careful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>caſt all your care on God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>for hee careth for all,</hi> and, <hi>caſt thy burden vpon the Lord &amp; he ſhall nouriſh thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.22.</note> 
               <hi>Delight thy ſelfe in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>and hee ſhall giue thee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21501:39"/>thine hearts deſire &amp;c.</hi> And applying to the heart ſuch experiments of Gods gracious ſupply of great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of his <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 16. and 17. 1. King. 17. Pſal. 147.9. Luk. 12.24.</note> 
               <hi>Elijah</hi> in the <hi>dearth</hi> and <hi>drought,</hi> &amp;c. That God that feedes the very Rauens, can cauſe the Rauens to feed the godly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Godlineſſe prouides for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the deſires by <hi>directing</hi> them <hi>to things aboue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Derect on of the deſire to heauenly things. Col. 3.2, 3. Phil 3.7, 8.</note> laied vp in Chriſt Ieſus, the godly mans <hi>gaine,</hi> and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently able to giue contentment. He is aboundantly rich,<note place="margin">Affatim Diues eſt, qui cum Chriſto paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Hieron. Ep ad H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liodord e vita ſolitaria.</note> that is poore with Chriſt, a repleniſhed treaſury of grace and glory: beyond whom a godly mans deſire can neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or enlarge it ſelfe: but muſt needs contentendly reſt in him, as in the vttermoſt period of all deſired, and al-ſufficient good.</p>
            <p>Now,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> to draw to an end of this branch of my diſcourſe, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of <hi>Contentment</hi> the <hi>attendant</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe.</hi> If this bee true indeed, as it is moſt true, that <hi>godlineſſe is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21501:39"/>of true contentment:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Why ſo many men liue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content.</note> what then is the cauſe of ſo many mens miſlike of their owne eſtates; of ſuch priuate murmurs, ſuch publike clamors, and common complaints which fill the eares both of God and men; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thoſe, who haue ſufficient to doe iuſtice to others, and to pay their debts: to refreſh themſelues and to maintaine their families: to fit them for Gods ſeruice in their lawfull callings?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth through want of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and how.</note>Surely the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>contentment</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe:</hi> and men therefore <hi>complaine</hi> of their owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as vnpleaſing and comfortleſſe, becauſe they haue not obtained the <hi>true-contenting</hi> gaine of piety and godlineſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some, through <hi>vngodlineſſe,</hi> haue plunged themſelues into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe and heart-breaking miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: and for want of godlineſſe, can finde no meanes of remedie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. 2. Others haue great <hi>wealth,</hi> but little <hi>contentment;</hi> becauſe they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21501:40"/>haue much <hi>goods,</hi> but little <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> great returne of earthly riches, but little increaſe of heauenly graces: great ſtore of pelfe, but little piety. For certaine it is, that according to the meaſure of godlineſſe is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of godly contentment. Little godlineſſe, little contentment: no godlineſſe, no <hi>true</hi> contentment: great godlineſſe, great contentment. Many complaine as well when they haue, as when they want; becauſe they want it, while, they haue it, as wanting godlineſſe which teacheth. 1. How to eſteeme it. 2. How to enioy it. 3. How to beſtow it. Yea, the more they haue, the leſſe they are ſatisfied: becauſe, the further they are from godlineſſe, the further from contentment. They greedily gape for more gaine without, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want due meaſure of godlineſſe within. For were they wel-ſtored of godlineſſe inwardly, they would not feele ſuch want of riches outwardly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21501:40"/>
               <note place="margin">Why ſome men liue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.</note>In the <hi>heart</hi> of euery godly man which is <hi>Deo plenum</hi> filled with (the grace of) God, there is little roome left, for theſe fraile and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, but it is <hi>contented</hi> with a ſmaller portion of them. The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man can find content in pouerty: the vngodly finds diſcontent in ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The godly man finds content in diſgrace. The vngodly, diſcontent in honour. The godly, content in paine: the vngodly, diſcontent in pleaſure. And, to omit the vngodly man, (who neuer enioyes any true, any ſound, any durable content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) the godly man findes plenty in pouertie; honour in diſgrace: pleaſure in paine: health in ſickneſſe: ſolace in ſadneſſe: life in death, and hope of future felicitie, in ſenſe of preſent miſerie. Godlineſſe made Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> in <hi>priſon</hi> (in the <hi>inner priſon</hi>) in the <hi>ſtockes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.24, 25</note> to <hi>ſing</hi> for ioy: while the vngodly Iewes were, at liberty, either ſleeping or ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or ſenſeleſſe of their preſent
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21501:41"/>ſinne and future miſerie. And the vnconuerted <hi>Iaylor was ready,</hi> for feare of their <hi>eſcape,</hi> to <hi>make away himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obiections anſwered. 2 Cor. 6.9.10.</note>And ſuppoſe a godly man bee in ſorrow: yet is he <hi>ſorrowfull, as alway reioycing:</hi> as <hi>chaſtened, yet not killed:</hi> as <hi>dying, yet behold he liueth: as hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet poſſeſſeth all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8,</note> Bee hee <hi>troubled on euery ſide, yet is he not diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: perplexed yet not in deſpaire: perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted yet not forſaken: caſt downe, yet not deſtroyed: dying for Ieſus,</hi> yet <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life from Ieſus.</hi> And though hee <hi>fall,</hi> yet the Lord ſhall <hi>raiſe</hi> him vp: <hi>Though he ſit in darkeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>yet the Lord ſhall bee a light vnto him. Weeping may endure for a night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> 
               <hi>but ioy commeth in the morning.</hi> And the more his former affliction increaſed, the more his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ioy aboundeth. Godlineſſe can mitigate and aſſwage the grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preſent afflictions, and make patient of change from better to worſe, in the fluent vncertainty of this outward eſtate and the power of godlineſſe is a ſoueraigne cordiall to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21501:41"/>cheere vp the ſpirits, and to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to counteruaile all aſſailing dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſiniſter or croſſe euents. So that it is the priuiledge of a truely godly and ſound hearted Chriſtian to <hi>reioyce in tribulation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.3. Rom. 8.31.32 &amp;c. 1 Cor. 15.55.56.57.</note> and to <hi>triumph</hi> ouer <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall enemies:</hi> ſo that he alone hath ſufficient cauſe to liue comfortably, and to applaud himſelfe in his happie condition, when all the world doth threaten, or is threatned, miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in the life of man.</note>Worthy were it to conſider for the commendation of godlineſſe, but too long to relate for want of time: how ſafely and comfortably, This godly contentment will cauſe men to walk in the golden mean between thoſe two fowle extremes of <hi>careleſſe neglect</hi> of that which they ought to take; and <hi>greedy graſping</hi> after that which they ought not to deſire. 1. A godly man dare neither liue out of a calling, nor neglect his duty in a gainfull courſe; becauſe he is godly. 2. Neither can he be greedy of gaine,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21501:42"/>and rent himſelfe with diſtractiue care, or vſe vnſeemely means to rake to himſelfe that which is not his; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is content with his owne. This conſtant endeauour is, not to decline either to the right hand or to the left: but to bound himſelf within the limits of Chriſtian prudence, and religious moderation. He accounts him rich, not who abounds in his wealth, but who is godly in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, not who hath his poſſeſſions enlarged, but who hath his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons moderated, and if the greedy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite be not ſatisfied; hee accounts the treaſures of <hi>Diues</hi> extreame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: and the penurie of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſufficient plentie. And maruails not that a godly <hi>Swaine</hi> can finde more content in his beggers cottage; then an vngodly <hi>Emperour</hi> in his princely Pallace. In a word: he can learne of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> with godly <hi>Saint Paul; in whatſoeuer eſtate he is, therewith to bee content,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>he knowes how to be abaſed, and how to abound: to be full, and to bee hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21501:42"/>to abound and to ſuffer neede. Hee can doe all things through Chriſt who ſtrengtheneth him:</hi> and through the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> which <hi>workes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment</hi> in him. The holy Teacher of wiſedome telles him, that, <hi>better is a little with the feare of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>then great treaſure &amp; trouble therwith.</hi> That <hi>a little which the righteous man hath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.16.</note> 
               <hi>is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the riches of many wicked.</hi> Not becauſe that <hi>leſſe</hi> which hee hath is <hi>better:</hi> but becauſe <hi>hee</hi> which hath that leſſe, is <hi>better.</hi> And as a godly man findes his holineſſe <hi>increaſed,</hi> ſo he eſteemes his eſtate <hi>bettered.</hi> And when hee knowes himſelfe <hi>perfectly holy:</hi> then ſhall he finde himſelfe <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly happy.</hi> And then, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhall he obtaine the full <hi>fruition</hi> of heauenly <hi>felicitie,</hi> when hee hath bid <hi>farewell,</hi> to all <hi>earthlie</hi> ſtore, and <hi>outward</hi> plentie. As his godlineſſe is a wel-ſpring of his contentment: ſo is his holineſſe a fore-runner of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.<note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> Oh let vs be godly, that we may be content: and holy, that wee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21501:43"/>may be happy. For true <hi>pietie</hi> brings wel-pleaſing ſufficiencie: and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>holineſſe,</hi> eternall <hi>bleſſedneſſe.</hi> And thus much of <hi>Contentment the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 3. gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall point<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of the great gaine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note>Time and deſire, now haſten vs forward vnto the attribute of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe attended of contentment: and that is <hi>Gaine. Godlineſſe</hi> with <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment</hi> is <hi>gaine,</hi> and this <hi>gaine</hi> is not ſmall, but <hi>Great.</hi> Godlineſſe with contentment is <hi>great</hi> gaine. Where vnder the borrowed termes of <hi>gaine</hi> and aduantage in <hi>trading</hi> and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique in the courſe of this world, the worth and excellency of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is magnifyed and extolled.</p>
            <p>Returne and increaſe in worldly profits is eſteemed gaine: and ſo it is, but not ſuch gaine as the profane Apoſtles did fondly <hi>ſuppoſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> as though the holy doctrine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and precious name of piety ſhould bee baſely proſtituted to ſerue this earthly commodity as though religion were to be a bawde
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21501:43"/>to couetouſneſſe, or an art in policy inuented to compaſſe this worldly profit. No, no, but yet the truth is; That 1. <hi>True godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>true</hi> gaine: 2. Yea <hi>great gaine:</hi> 3. Yea <hi>the</hi> great gaine or <hi>greateſt gaine of all.</hi> And here are three points, and as it were three precious pearles, found out by our holy Apoſtle, in turning ouer the dung-hill of thoſe profane Apoſtles, who abuſed religion to filthy lucre. And theſe are three linkes in a chaine of gold, one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linked within another, which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they may be diſtinctly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, yet can they not well be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately handled. For when I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that <hi>godlineſſe is gaine,</hi> I inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate withall, that it is <hi>great gaine,</hi> and when I auouch, that <hi>godlineſſe is great gaine;</hi> I further inſinuate, that it is the <hi>greateſt gaine of all.</hi> In one word then, Godlineſſe is true gaine, inualuable, and incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or more diſtinctly thus. 1. True <hi>godlineſſe is true gaine.</hi> 2. True <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21501:44"/>is great gaine.</hi> 3. True <hi>godlineſſe is the greateſt gaine of all,</hi> and of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Godlineſſe is true gaine.</note>True <hi>Godlineſſe is true gaine.</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe as it is a diuine habite of grace, wrought in the heart of man, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſteeme in it ſelfe, though not eſteemed: commendable in it ſelfe, though not commended, apearle of price, a treaſure very rich.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Naz.</note> It is <hi>profit indeede to get gaine into the ſoule.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Verae diuitiae non opes ſunt, ſed virtutes. Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Vertue not wealth is the true riches.</hi> So gracious is vertue in the eye of the worſt, that it can extort from the vileſt man an approbation of it true goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Heathen <hi>wiſe</hi> in their three orders of their<note n="c" place="margin">Bona.</note> 
               <hi>goods.</hi> (1. Of body: as health, ſtrength, beauty. 2. Of Fortune (as they termed them) as riches, lands, treaſures. 3. Of the minde: as knowledge of arts and tongues, wiſdome, vertue) placed vertue in their higheſt ranke of all; Wealth in the loweſt. This ſcarce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the name of good; as vnable
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21501:44"/>to make the owner good. That of large extent, and moſt diuine; as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it ſelfe to make man happy. If they ſo highly eſteemed of the <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of <hi>vertue,</hi> little better, indeed, then <hi>ſhining vice:</hi> where ſhall wee place the ſubſtance, or vertue it ſelfe, truely and indeed diuine and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly? which whoſoeuer hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; ſurely enioyceth, oh happy he truly &amp; bleſſed! The wiſe man thus ſpeaketh, inſpired by Gods ſpirit: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that findeth wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>and the man that getteth vnderſtanding. For the merchandiſe of it is better then the merchandiſe of ſiluer: and the gaine thereof then fine gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſumme of ſiluer, no maſſe of gold, is ſo <hi>true</hi> a <hi>gaine,</hi> as vertue and godlineſſe. Gold and ſiluer what are they? Their matter is mud, of the baſeſt element. Their greateſt eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from the folly of the vaineſt men. Yet if this mire and mud (condenſated by heate of the Sunne, and influence of the heauens, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21501:45"/>by the heate of the fire, inſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the image and inſcription of the King, attained &amp; purchaſed by labour and induſtry,) be accounted truely <hi>gaine,</hi> and a bleſſing of God, as indeed it is; What then ſhall wee ſay of this <hi>true pearle</hi> of <hi>pietie,</hi> which is not digged out of any earthly mine, but fetched downe from the higheſt heauens: not of mire and mud, but of diuine of-ſpring: not generated by the heate of this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sunne, or inferior cauſe, but through diuine influence of Gods eternall ſpirit: not droſſie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, but cleane, and ſincere: not bearing the ſtampe, and inſcription of mortall man, but the image and ſimilitude of the immortall God? The hauing whereof will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enrich him, but transforme him into the glorious ſimilitude of the inuiſible King of heauen: whoſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage inſtamped in mans heart by creation, conſiſted in conformity with him in diuine graces and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21501:45"/>which are ſo many parts and parcels of the habite of godlineſſe? Surely, we can ſay no leſſe of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> but that it deſerues the name, and title, of <hi>true gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Godlineſſe is great gaine: and how.</note>As <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>true</hi> (and as I might haue ſaid <hi>Great</hi>) <hi>gaine</hi> as it is (in it ſelfe) a diuine habite of grace, in it ſelfe conſidered; ſo is it <hi>great gaine</hi> indeede, as it intiteleth and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſteth into further aduantage, in that it <hi>hath the promiſes of the life that now is and of that, which is to come.</hi> 1. Tim. 4 8. Of life naturall, and life ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all returne of godlineſſe.</note>The firſt and chiefeſt part and parcell of that rich <hi>returne,</hi> which godlineſſe by Gods promiſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in, is that heauenly reuenue of rich holineſſe and happineſſe which belong to a life <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> both this of <hi>grace</hi> and that other of <hi>glory.</hi> And here wee muſt know that this promiſe is made, and made good in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from whom as our <hi>Head,</hi> wee deriue our <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> and in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21501:46"/>whom we finde all our treaſures of <hi>goodneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt our treaſury emptied (as it were) himſelfe, to repleniſh vs: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came poore to make vs rich. Poore in outward eſtate, to make vs rich in our inward condition: poore in our nature, that we might be rich in his grace: poore temporally, to make vs rich eternally. In Chriſt we gaine ſufficient treaſures of <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> to diſcharge our debt of diſobedience.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30. 2. Cor. 5.21. Hebr. 9.14. &amp; 10.14.</note> The al-ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his <hi>death</hi> to ranſome vs from the death of ſinne.<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.5, 6. 1. Pet. 2.24. Col. 2, 3. 2. Cor. 5.18, 19.</note> The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue our folly and deformities. Wee gaine <hi>reconciliation</hi> with God,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.12. Hebr. 10.20.22.</note> in ſted of emnity; <hi>acceſſe</hi> to God, in ſtead of alienation from God;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1. Rom. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>Peace</hi> of conſcience, in ſtead of terrors; <hi>Ioy</hi> in the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> in ſted of ſorrow in our ſoule;<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17. 1. Ioh. 1.4.</note> comfortable <hi>hope</hi> in ſted of dreadfull deſpaire. In Chriſt wee gaine priuiledge of <hi>Son-ſhip</hi> and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall adoption,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.2. Ehpeſ. 1.5. Apoc. 1.6.</note> title to a <hi>crowne,</hi> and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21501:46"/>fellowſhip in a <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>communion</hi> with God our <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.3.</note> the <hi>ſonne</hi> (himſelfe) our redeemer, and the holy ſpirit our bleſſed guide, and ſtrong ſupporter, ſweet comforter, &amp; perfect ſanctifier. In Chriſt we gaine the <hi>prayers</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> yet <hi>liuing</hi> with vs: the <hi>loue</hi> of the <hi>Saints glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> before vs:<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.14.</note> the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> working for vs, grace in earth: and glory in heauen. In Chriſt our gaine is ſuch, as that we ſhall haue all loſſes recompenſed; all wants ſupplied; al curſes remoued, al croſſes ſanctified; all graces increaſed: all hopes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: all promiſes accompliſhed; all bleſſedneſſe procured, Satan conquered, <hi>death</hi> deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Oſe. 13.14. 1. Cor. 15.54.55.</note> the graue ſweetened, corruption aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſanctification perfected, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen opened for our happy entrance. <hi>Lift vp your heads,</hi> Oh yee heauenly <hi>gates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.7.</note> 
               <hi>and bee yee lifted vp yee euerlaſting doores, that the King of glory may bring vs in.</hi> Now when Heauen ſhall be our gaine, what can be our loſſe?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21501:47"/>Vnleſſe we looſe our teares, wiped from our eyes? Vnleſſe wee looſe our ſorrowes, expelled from our hearts? Vnleſſe we looſe our daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, remoued from our perſons? Vnleſſe we looſe our infirmities, our deformities, our tranſitory eſtate, our temporall condition (which we account for precious) to change them for permanent and eternall happineſſe? And what is, or rather is not the gaine of godlineſſe, when it hath brought man to happineſſe? That, indeed, which <hi>no</hi> mortall <hi>eye hath euer ſeene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 64 4. 1. Cor. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>no eare heard,</hi> no tongue vttered, no <hi>heart conceiued.</hi> What hand can meaſure the boundes of infinitie? What minde can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the yeeres of eternitie? What hand, what minde, can meaſure, can number, the vnmeaſurable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and innumerable number of the wealth and treaſures of piety and godlineſſe? Oh that I had the tongues of the glorious Angels, in ſome ſort, for your ſakes to vtter?
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21501:47"/>Oh, rather, that you had the hearts of the glorified Saints, in ſome little ſmall meaſure to conceiue, of ſome part and parcell of this ſpirituall gaine of godlineſſe! But this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sunne doth ſo dazle my weake eyes, this bottomleſſe depth doth ſo ouerwhelme my ſhallow heart, and the ſurpaſſing greatneſſe of theſe rich treaſures doth ſo euery way o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharge mee, that I muſt needes ſtand ſilent, amazed and aſtoniſhed, at the ſerious conſideration of the exceeding aboundant excellencie of theſe reuenues of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. The tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall returne of godlineſſe.</note>As thoſe who finde their tender eye-ſight dazeled by gazing direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the body of the Sunne, doe learne to behold it in ſome oblique reflexion (as we obſerue the ecclipſe in a baſen of water) euen ſo let vs perceiuing the eye of our mind now dimmed and dazeled with the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding brightneſſe of the gaine of godlineſſe, in the chiefeſt glory ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) looke vpon it more indirectly in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21501:48"/>the ſecondary reflexions of earthly bleſſings, which (as you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) were entayled on godlineſſe by the gracious promiſe of God.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath the promiſe of the life that now is.</hi> Whatſoeuer true gaine can bee found in this life, it is annexed to godlineſſe as an <hi>auctarie</hi> or <hi>appendant,</hi> and is as an <hi>ouerplus</hi> or <hi>ouer-meaſure caſt</hi> vnto him,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> who ſhall <hi>firſt haue ſought the kingdome of God and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 1.2.</note> conueighed by Chriſt the <hi>heire of all</hi> vnto him that is truly god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or truly beleuing.</p>
            <p>A godly man hath <hi>two treaſuries,</hi> without him of gainefull reuenues. <hi>Heauen aboue</hi> a repleniſhed treaſurie of bleſſings ſpirituall:<note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>and Earth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a wel-furniſhed ſtore-houſe of benefits temporall. As thoſe aboue are beſtowed onely vpon a godly man: ſo theſe below are by moſt iuſt title to deſcend to him, who is <hi>fellow heire with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> the heire of al things. Strangers may haue ſome portion of them, but the right of inheritance
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21501:48"/>belongs to the ſons of God. Riches and honour, delights and pleaſures, life and length of daies,<note place="margin">Prou 3.16.17 &amp; 8.18. Deut. 28. Pſ. 1 12.2.3.</note> ſeed and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie are entailed to ſuch as are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeuing, and feare the Lord. And howſoeuer the vngodly man may lay ſome claime vnto them, and that by ſome kinde of right from God; (as a preſeruer of nature,<note place="margin">How a godles man may lay claime to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</note> a ſuſtainer of his creature, a maintainer of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, a rewarder of induſtry, as a god of mercy alluring by benefits, and a god of iuſtice to make men, refuſing his mercy, excuſeleſſe.) And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer no man can deſpoil him of them, without <hi>great ſinne,</hi> yet can he not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy them with any <hi>great</hi> comfort; as wanting the <hi>beſt</hi> title, through the want of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now then if any man bee poſſeſſed with an ouerweening conceit, of the exceeding woorth of worldly gaine: be it knowen vnto him that whatſoeuer it is, rightly to waigh it, and properly to ſpeake of it, it is all, and onely entailed to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. The <hi>beſt</hi> title being loſt in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21501:49"/>reſtored by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for <hi>godlineſſe hath the promiſes both of this life preſent and of that which is to come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8. Leuit. 26. Deut. 28.</note> vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the threats, and curſes of them both.</p>
            <p>Yet if any be ſo retchleſly pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh and peruerſe, that hee will ſtill contend: that the gaine of the world belongs <hi>aſwell</hi> to the vngodly, as godly, as <hi>de facto,</hi> ſo <hi>de iure.</hi> To leaue the deciding of that controuerſie as a fit Niſiprius for the great Iudge of all, at the generall Aſſiſes, be it gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him that his claime is as good: yet his gaine is ſtill leſſe then the godly mans is, for howſoeuer the gaine of the world be granted to bee great, yet <hi>the gaine of godlineſſe is of all the greatest</hi> gaine. And in this I am to ſpend, the laſt part of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Godlineſſe is the greateſt gaine of all.</note>That the <hi>gaine of Godlineſſe</hi> ſhould <hi>be of all the greateſt gaine,</hi> it is holden a Paradox and a ſtrange aſſertion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many in the world. The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe worldling, take him in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21501:49"/>would be loath to be thought ſo fooliſh, as to exchange his gaine with a godly mans. His eyes are ſo blinded, and his heart ſo poſſeſſed with the ſuppoſed worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of this earthly gaine; that hee hath neither eyes to ſee, nor heart to eſteeme the price of the heauenly. Yea the euer-thirſting deſire, and reſtleſſe endeauour, after that gaine of the world, and the careleſſe neglect and retchleſſe contempt of this of <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> which is ſeene in the moſt, doeth plainely demonſtrate that, of all, the feweſt doe account of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> as of all the beſt, and <hi>greateſt gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betweene the gaine of the world and the gaine of godlineſſe.</note>Let vs now enter into a compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue diſcourſe betweene that <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gaine</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> (which a godles worldling may haue in common with the godly) and the <hi>ſpirituall gaine: of godlineſſe</hi> (which a godly man doth alone poſſeſſe, beſides his part and portion in that other:) and it ſhall ſoone appeare (I hope to our profit)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21501:50"/>that the gaine of godlineſſe is far the greater gaine.<note place="margin">1 Generall and that in. 1 Profits of the worldling.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. And <hi>worldlings</hi> gaine may be great in deede, ſhall we (to helpe him) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him poſſeſſed, of pleaſant gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, fruitfull orchards, fieldes and vineyards, faire pallaces, and large prouinces, ſhall we ſuppoſe him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with wealth at will,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> in ſtore and aboundance of gold as ſiluer; of ſiluer,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 1.15</note> as <hi>ſtones;</hi> of pearles, as pibbles in the ſtreetes: yet were the gaine of godlineſſe greater then this: and a godly man farre richer then he.<note place="margin">Profites of the Godly man.</note> For Chriſt the <hi>Lord</hi> of all is his <hi>Lord-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,</hi> and the infinite fulneſſe of his al-ſufficient deity the ſtore that's laid vp in the godly mans treaſurie, ſome Iewels (which Chriſt doth heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow) are theſe;<note place="margin">Prou. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdome, which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then fine gold, more precious then the Rubies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 28.</note> 
               <hi>faith</hi> which is precious, <hi>loue</hi> of God, <hi>hope</hi> of glory, <hi>pietie, righteouſnes, holineſſe,</hi> all <hi>heauenly vertues,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine graces, treaſures inualuable, of incomparable woorth. And what
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21501:50"/>were thoſe worldly goodes in the iudgement of the wiſeſt among the heathen? ſurely but <hi>indifferent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Peripatet. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Platonic. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Zeno. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Eth.</note> 
               <hi>Neither good nor euill.</hi> Or <hi>good, not</hi> ſo much in their <hi>owne nature,</hi> as in the <hi>iudgement of men.</hi> Others accounted them, <hi>vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſome good end.</hi> Or let them bee <hi>good,</hi> as indeed they are, the <hi>good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God:</hi> yet are they good things but of the <hi>loweſt rancke of good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bona minima. Aug. retract. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> The couetous worldling may eſteeme wealth the moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> good. And <hi>ſiluer to him may be blood and ſoule:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eurip.</note> and when he hath loſt his goods hee may <hi>hange himſelfe,</hi> as hauing loſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready his <hi>life, layd</hi> vp in his <hi>goods.</hi> Let all bee <hi>trifles compared</hi> with his <hi>gold.</hi> Yea let him ſay to the wedge of gold thou art my hope,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Menand.</hi>
               </note> and eſteeme ſiluer and gold his moſt <hi>profitable gods.</hi> Yet what of all this? is he therefore rich? The godly hath wealth which is a <hi>God</hi> in deed, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> is his <hi>gaine;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> is his <hi>portion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 3 7. Ier. 10.16.</note> It is not good ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to be wealthy; but to be weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in <hi>good</hi> things; eſpecially in <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21501:51"/>who is <hi>goodneſſe</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Let the worldlings wealth bee graced with <hi>honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the worldling.</note> backed with <hi>Empire, and authority royall.</hi> Let him ſit on the Throne, weare the crowne, ſaay the ſcepter, preſcribe lawes, command, forbid, reward, puniſh: Let him be able to helpe his friends, to hurt his foes, to aduance his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorites, to debaſe his oppoſites: Let him be royally attended, highly honoured, lowly ſaluted; as victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, wiſe, prudent, politique: Let him be heartily loued, and loyally embraced, as the piller of the weale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, father of his countrie, patterne of antiquity,<note place="margin">Amor &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciae generis humani.</note> loue and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of wholem man-kinde, with <hi>Titus Veſpaſian:</hi> Let him be eſteemed the light of the eyes,<note place="margin">Bonus Deus Conſtantinum Imperatorem tantis terrenis impleuit mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, quanta optare nullus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deret. Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> ioy of the heart, breath of the noſtrils of many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of ſubiectes. And to conclude: <hi>Let him be ſo fully repleniſhed with ſuch earthly good things, as no mortall man durſt wiſh ſo great</hi> (As <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi>) Yet
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21501:51"/>if in all this proſperity hee be but a meere worldling, the godly mans game is greater then this; ſhall hee bee likewiſe inueſted with his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſoueraignty.<note place="margin">The honour of the godly.</note> For hee ſhall be adorned with the glorious robes of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly triumph ouer the world, fleſh, ſinne, and ſatan: preſcribe lawes to inordinate affections; be ctowned a King in heauen,<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.6.</note> attended of the Angels, honoured of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, liue in neereſt communion with God himſelfe, enioy his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.32. Mat. 25.34.</note> and partake with him in an eternall <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Pleaſures of the worlding.</note>3 Laſtly, let the worldlings wealth be not onely adorned with honour, but ſweetened with <hi>pleaſures.</hi> Let him enioy the ſweete comforts of health of body, tranquillity of mind, faithfull, faire, and fruitfull wife, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and obedient ſonnes and daughters, truſty ſeruants, good neighbours, kinde acquaintance, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſtable friends. Let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21501:52"/>dainty meates, ſweete-ſounding muſicke,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.10.</note> and all the delights of the ſonnes of men.<note place="margin">Pleaſures of the godly.</note> 
               <hi>Yet is</hi> the <hi>godly mans</hi> eſtate far better then this: for hee doth moſt comfortably enioy the ſweeteſt delights and comforts of the ſoule: due ſubmiſſion of body to ſoule, of ſoule to God: peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ioy in the holy Ghoſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in affliction, ſtrength in tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, life in death, and neuer-fading delights, and riuers of pleaſures; the ioy and ſolace of a Sonne of God, of a ſpouſe of Chriſt, of an inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of heauen, and of an enioyer of God, in fulneſſe of ioy, and vnchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable glory.</p>
            <p>Oh conſider (I beſeech you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in the Lord) conſider and weigh theſe things a little. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is worthy your deepeſt medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">2. A ſpeciall compariſon of the gaine of the worlding, and godlie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> Conſider (I ſay) and you ſhall aſſuredly finde; that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt gaine of the worldling is very ſmal: the ſmalleſt of the godly is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great. This of worth, that worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21501:52"/>
The greateſt <hi>gaine</hi> the <hi>worldling</hi> can enioy, is but <hi>outward and ſuperficiall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine is but outward and ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</note> ſeruing onely for the vſe of humane and corporall life, which conſiſtes in coniunction of ſoule and body vnited alone by the bond of nature: but the gaine of the godly is inward and ſubſtantiall,<note place="margin">The godly mans inward and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall.</note> of vſe to a life di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and ſpirituall, which conſiſtes in coniunction of the whole per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, both ſoule and body, with God, and that by a bond of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. That frees but from ſome outward euill: as pouertie, the leaſt of euils, which one rich and ready friend may eaſily reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. From diſgrace, which may ſometimes prooue glorious, as for ſuch cauſe, or with ſuch perſons, as where diſgrace is honour. From outward paine, which may worke vs pleaſure, and prepare for greater ioy and ſolace. But this freeth from the greateſt euils: from ſpirituall beggery, ignominy, miſery, and makes rich within, glorious, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21501:53"/>well appayed. And what were it to haue a purple coate, &amp; a polluted conſcience? a gay gowne, and a ſick heart? a bed of gold, and a diſeaſed minde? a full cheſt, and an emptie ſoule? afaire face, and foule affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? to gliſter in iewels, and to bee filthy in manners? to bee in grace with men, and diſgrace with God? One <hi>dramme</hi> of that true inwarde gaine is farre more worth then a <hi>thouſand</hi> worlds.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine is mutable and vncertaine.</note>The worldlings gaine is mutable and vncertaine, and ſoone, God knowes, is changed for a loſſe! it is conſtant in nothing, but in <hi>mutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.17.</note> the inſeparable property of all earthly vanities. Now a man is rich, preſently poore: now in honour, anon in diſgrace: now in pleaſure, euen now in paine.<note place="margin">Prou. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>Riches take their wings and flie away:</hi> honour with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery croſſe blaſt is blowen away: and pleaſures melt in the taſte, as dew before the morning ſun. How ſoone are our feaſtes turned into
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21501:53"/>faſtes, and our ſweeteſt ſongs into mournefull lamentations!<note place="margin">Lament 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>They that did feede delicately are deſolate in the ſtreetes, and they that were brought vp in ſcarlet embrace the dunghill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Poet. <hi>Inſtin. hiſtor. lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> How ſoone fayre-ſhining Fortunes fall and faile! Renowmed <hi>Xerxes,</hi> the fame of antiquity, paſſed ouer into Greece, in paſſing ſtate and pride, but returned home in great baſeneſſe and feare. As he went, he couered the ſeas, with his gallant ſhippes: but as hee came, was ſcarce prouided of a meane fiſhers boate. Hee went guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an army ſo huge and mighty, that it emptied deepe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, did eate vp large countries, and was a burden to the very earth: but he returned not attended of a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting boy. And he who of late was the terrour of the world a broade, was preſently in contempt with the meaneſt of his houſe at home.</p>
            <p>Would you ſee an admirable ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of humane mutability?<note place="margin">Munſter. Chronol. de Tureis. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> caſt your eyes vpon <hi>Baiazet</hi> that terrible
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21501:54"/>
               <hi>Turke,</hi> and cruell ſcourge of Greece. How ſoone was he ſubdued by <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlane</hi> the <hi>Tartar,</hi> led about on a ſcaffold, as a beaſt, in a chayne of gold, and carried with him abroad, in all his expeditions, as a foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole to tread on, when hee moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on horſe-backe, and as a dogge to picke crummes from vnder his table. And what became of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of this cruell conquerour, who in deuiliſh pride diſdayning the name of man, would bee ſtiled, <hi>the wrath of God,</hi> the vaſtity and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the world? Hee left his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſtuffed with wealth and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to be diſſipated and extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by his diſagreeing ſonnes. Read the hiſtorie of <hi>Adoni-bezek.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 1.6, 7.</note> Who hauing in his pride and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cauſed. 70. <hi>Kings, hauing their thumbes and great toes cut off to</hi> bee g'ad like whelpes to <hi>gather crummes from vnder his table:</hi> hee was <hi>requited</hi> of God, and brought to like miſery, and experienced the mutability of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21501:54"/>all earthly ſtates. What ſhould I mention the known Hiſtory of <hi>Croe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herodet. Clio. ſine lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> who in the top of his proſperity, would needes haue <hi>Solon</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him happy; but anon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-topt by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and ſet on a pile of wood to bee burnt, (finding his ſudden change from ſuppoſed hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to certaine calamity) cryed out in griefe and ſorrow of heart, <hi>Oh Solon, Solon, Solon!</hi> The cauſe of this out-cry when <hi>Cyrus</hi> vnderſtood, he gaue him his life, and intreated him kindly, fearing the like miſery to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hered. ib.</note> as knowing the <hi>inſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of humane affaires,</hi> and <hi>calamity whereto all men are ſubject,</hi> as the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian doth well obſerue. Of all the daies of this mortall life the latter findes him not as the former left him.</p>
            <p>No maruell though <hi>Tiberius</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> refuſed the ſtile of <hi>Pater pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae, father of his country,</hi> on this ground of vncertainty of all theſe earthly thing, <hi>ſaying. All mortall mens
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21501:55"/>
                  <hi>eſtates are vncertaine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cuncta morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium incerta, quantoque plus adeptus foret, tanto ſe magis in lubrico dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taus. Tacit. annal. lib. <hi>1.</hi> De Ciuit. Dei. l. <hi>1. c.1. Eſa. 28.4.</hi>
                  </note> man hath gotten, the more ſlippery is his condition.</hi> Let me in one word (with Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) ſpeake thus of them all: <hi>Sunt omnia terrena cacumina tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porali mobilitaie nutantia. All terrene heights doe reele with temporall mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</hi> Heare the Lord himſelfe: <hi>The glorious beautie</hi> (of all earthly excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency) <hi>which is on the head of the fatte valley, ſhall bee as a fading flower, and as the haſtie fruit before the Summer: which when hee that looketh vpon it, ſeeth it, while it is yet in his hand he eateth it vp.</hi> The beſt ſettled ſtates grow ſoone vnſetled: and theſe <hi>adamantine</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes haue foundations of <hi>ſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The godly mans chief gaine is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable and certaine.</note>But the choiſe gaine of godlineſſe is immutable and certaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a Kingdome vnſhaken.</hi> The heauenly calling and ſpecial guifts thereof are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr. 12.28. Rom. 11.29.</hi> Beza in Locum Nec prodi nec perdi poſſunt. Aug de ciuit. deil l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Such as whereof <hi>God can neuer repent himſelfe,</hi> that hee gaue them, or repenting take them backe againe. Theſe good things can <hi>neither bee betrayed nor loſt.</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:21501:55"/>The ſame God that gaue them will ſtill maintaine them; and ſecond his kindnes with a ſupply of newgrace, <hi>This grace of God hath no end, knowes no ſtint.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſt. in Rom. 5</note> Temptation may obſcure the outward gloſſe, but cannot hurt the in ward ſubſtance. Some leaues may fall, and ſome fruit may fade: but the feede and roote of grace ſhall ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine. Some ſhowres and cloudes are heere below: but aboue theſe mountaines there are no clouds; in the higheſt heauens is no mutability. But <hi>in that day ſhall the Lord of Hoſtes be for a crowne of glory, and for a durable diademe of neuer-fading beauty vnto the reſidue of his people.</hi> Eſay. 28.5.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine is for a ſhort time.</note>The worldlings gaine, though it were firme and certaine, yet is it but for a <hi>time.</hi> The longeſt terme is but the <hi>ſhort life of man,</hi> and what is the life of man? <hi>ſhort and vncertaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob. 14.1.2.</hi> breuis eſt vita, &amp; ipſa breuitas ſemper incerta. Aug. de verb. dom. ſerm. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> As graſſe in the field, ſoone withering: <hi>as a flower</hi> in the garden, ſoone fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: as a bubble on the water, ſoone falling: as an vnconſtant ſhadow,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21501:56"/>ſoone flitting: as a drowſie mans dreame, ſoone vaniſhing. A gnat, a flie, ill ſmell, moiſture of dew, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted blaſt, or ſuſpenſe of ſhort breath diſlodgeth the ſoule of body and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſſeſſeth both body and ſoule of the world, and heere is farewell to all; and thus all this gaine is gone. Vnleſſe he hope his name ſhall liue in the mouthes of commenders; which gaine (if but for worldly reſpects) is <hi>a ſmoke of no weight,</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ballance: or to purchaſe a tombe for his liueleſſe carcaſſe, which ſomtimes proclaimes to the world his not yet-dying ambition; and whereon oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for his ill demeanure, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamped the characters of long-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting diſgrace.<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtant. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi> Tacit. Annal. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the great (as likewiſe <hi>Caeſar Germanicus</hi>) liued but 32 yeeres: his raigne was little more then one third of that: In his ſhort raigne, hee was glorious, for ſlaughter and crueltie: and withall ignominious, for reuelling, and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe. The <hi>glorious raigne</hi> of <hi>Cyrus</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21501:56"/>ended in an <hi>ignominious death,</hi> hee was conquered by a <hi>woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Conſtant. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> Thomyris. Satia te ſaengui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, quem ſitiſti, cuiuſque inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiabilis ſemper fuiſti. Iuſtin. hiſtor. lib <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and his head was caſt into a veſſell of blood, with vile exprobration of his bloudy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. Yea, and all godly Kings, and religious Emperours muſt part with this part of their aduantage &amp; gaine; and muſt truſt to that more refined portion of their wealth,<note place="margin">The godly mans gaine is for euer. Prou. 8.18.</note> that proper gaine of godlineſſe, which is <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>durable;</hi> not dying with the body or left below; but liuing with the ſoule through indiſſoluble vnion and communion with God in Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Ioh. 2.17.</hi> Bona huius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt, vaneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo tranſeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: futurae ſine fine manſura. Aug. de ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the wel-ſpring of life to the ſoule, while the body lies in the graue, &amp; who ſhall raiſe the bodie to partake in glory. When the world is <hi>paſſed and vaniſhed</hi> away: this gaine ſhall be conſtant, for euer remaining. That gaine is like a ſudden ſhowre, which ſpeedily falles, and haſtilie is gone: this like a wel-ſpring or flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fountaine euer ſtreaming and ſtreaming vnto all eternity.<note n="*" place="margin">Facile conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit omnia, qui ſe ſemper cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat eſſe moritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Hieron. op. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> He will eaſily contemne that earthly gaine,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21501:57"/>who alwaies thinkes that once hee muſt needes die: &amp; euer highly prize that heauenly wealth, which ſhall make him euer bleſſed, &amp; neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him. For it were much to paſſe from ſmall wealth to extreame penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: from ſhort honour to eternall diſgrace: and from momentany plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to euerlaſting paine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine is mixt and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with loſſe.</note>The worldlings gaine is not ſound and ſincere, but <hi>mingled and infected</hi> with ſome attendant <hi>loſſe,</hi> heer's no good entire, without ſome loſſe: no commoditie, without ſome incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniency.<note place="margin">Ipſemundi qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſcunque ſtatus plus anxietat is, quam iucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis habet: &amp; ſi qua tamen eſt, praeterit iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunditas non reditura, &amp; manet anxietas non relictura. Bern. ep. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> The beſt prouided earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtate hath more anxiety (or vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) then ſweetneſſe, and the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if any, paſſeth away not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne; the anxiety remaineth and will not goe away. So that a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is moſt-what affected, if not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, with vngratefull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſome euill paſt: or vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſenſe of ſome euill preſent: or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractiue feare of euill to come. And man is naturally affected more with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21501:57"/>euill, then good: with paine, then pleaſure. A ſhort ſickeneſſe more affecteth then long health: ſmall paine ſwalloweth vp much pleaſure: a little diſgrace defaceth much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: and a little loſſe of wealth ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained doth more diſquiet, then much wealth retained doth content. Now no worldling ſo happy, but feeles ſome calamity: none gets ſuch gaine, but meetes with ſome loſſe, and this loſſe doth make the gaine to ſeeme but ſmall.<note place="margin">The godly mans gaine is ſound and ſincere.</note> But the <hi>gaine</hi> of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> (principally after this life when the chiefe returne thereof comes in) is throughly <hi>ſound</hi> and truly <hi>ſincere,</hi> without mixture of loſſe, or concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of euill.<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.3.5.</note> Ther's no vngratefull remembrance of euill paſt, but ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full triumph ouer euils eſcaped. Ther's no vnpleaſant ſenſe of euill preſent, but ſweete and ſincere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleaſure. Ther's no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull feare of euill to come, but ſafe ſecurity, and interrupted tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21501:58"/>
               <note place="margin">5. The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine is imperfect and cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note>The greateſt worldlings gaine (ſuppoſe it greater then euer it can be) onely good without poſitiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: yet is is <hi>imperfect</hi> and <hi>cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> the minde of man. The deſire of man doth farre exceede the modell, and compaſſe of all inferior obiects: they are all too ſcant and narrow to fill mans heart. So that the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is vſually much diſquieted with diſcontent at the imperfection of ſome good attained: or with langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing hope of ſome good expected. Hee often deuoures that in hope, whereof he miſſeth: or if his happe be ſo good, as to hit on it; yet is his ioy farre paſt, before the thing bee had, or if it be had with expected ioy, yet is it enioyed with leſſe then expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted comfort; while it melteth and diſſolueth in the very taſte. Hence it comes to paſſe, that a <hi>Godleſſe</hi> man (who hath gained the world, but not godlineſſe, and therewithall godly contentment) is like to a <hi>ſicke</hi> man tumbling on his couch, and finding
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21501:58"/>all repoſe wearineſſe; tediouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing with things preſent, and longingly deſyring things to come. Stilthe deſire exceeds the fruition, &amp; ſo the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill wants contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yea and though the preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire be granted, yet is not the minde herewith ſatisfied: for men vſe highly to account the things they would haue, and when they haue them, count them little worth. And though they haue neuer ſo much, yet be their any thing elſe which they cannot haue; the want of that more troubleth them, then the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of al they haue, can pleaſe them. Yet more then this: let a meere godleſſe worldling haue what hee can deſire, yet can he but <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> that he might haue more: that vaine and fooliſh <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> will much detract from his good contentment.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more? The heart of man is, for poſſibility of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, ſo vnlimited, that no earthly thing can fully repleniſh it. <hi>All may
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21501:59"/>bee in it,<note place="margin">Anima ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis ad imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem-Dei facta, caeteris omnibus occupari poteſt, repleri non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Serm dedicat. <hi>Eſa. 28.20. Eſa. 29.8.</hi>
                  </note> but cannot fill it.</hi> This <hi>bed is ſhorter then that a man can ſtretch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on it: this couering is narrower then that hee can wrappe himſelfe in it.</hi> A godleſſe worlding ſhall be euen as <hi>when an hungry man dreameth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he eateth: but hee awaketh, and his ſoule is empty; or as when a thirſty man dreameth hee drinketh, but hee awaketh, and behold hee is faint, and his ſoule hath appetite in it.</hi> The reaſon is: God made the reaſonable ſoule in his owne image,<note place="margin">Animam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalem-Dei ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacem quicquid Deo minus eſt nonimplebit. Bern. Serm. dedieat.</note> in ſome ſenſe, capable of himſelfe (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes of the vnlimited diſire of the ſoule) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whatſoeuer is leſſe then God cannot fill it full.</p>
            <p>But the gaine of godlineſſe is <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>littlely perfect;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The godly mans gaine is perfect and can giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note> and ſit alone to giue <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment;</hi> as being the gaine, not of earth alone, but the heauen alone, but of him alſo who filles both earth and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Ier. 23, 24.</note> and heart and all; euen <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> with the infinitenes of his aboundant ſtore, as far as mans heart
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21501:59"/>is capable of that which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth, when he ſhalbe all in all. Then alſo ſhall the deſire of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified ſoule be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully enlarged, and the deſire enlarged, ſhall be fully contanted. Where betweene tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall good things obſerue this difference. Thoſe (temporall) are moſt deſired before they be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and when they are enioyed, are leſſe accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of (which becauſe they are imperfect, giue not full content:) but theſe (eternall) are leſſe eſteemed before they be attained, but aſſoone as they are taſted, they are more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently loued: the more ardently lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the more earneſtly are they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: and moſt of all admired, when moſt aboundantly enioyed: and that in that bleſſed kingdome of heauen, where our loue ſhall enioy aſmuch (if not more) as our minde can conceiue,<note place="margin">Eſa. 64.4.</note> our heart deſire, our faith beleeue, or hope expect. And what is that gaine which can giue full contentment, but this infinite
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21501:60"/>aboundance of incorruptible good?</p>
            <p>The worldings gaine <hi>expoſeth</hi> to many <hi>daungers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine expoſeth to daungers.</note> but godlineſſe <hi>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> how to <hi>eſcape</hi> them all. Thoſe daungers doe meete with (if not enuiron) this worldly trader on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide: both in <hi>getting,</hi> and <hi>keeping,</hi> and <hi>parting</hi> with it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. In getting.</note>Such is the baſeneſſe of this world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaine, that it may be gotten, not onely by Truth and Vertue, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by Fraud and Falſhood.<note place="margin">Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>5.12.</hi>
               </note> Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the bounty and bleſſing of God, but alſo by proffer and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the deuill, who proclaimes himſelfe <hi>owner of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 4.</note> 
               <hi>with the glory thereof,</hi> and <hi>beſtower of them on whom hee will.</hi> And the fayreſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the courſe of trading is ſayd to bring in, moſt commonly, ſuch ſlender returne: that it is growen a prouerbe among the multitude: That, <hi>plaine dealing is a Iewel, but hee that vſeth it ſhall die a begger.</hi> And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are of minde, eſpecially tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that, <hi>if they deale truely they ſhall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21501:60"/>not bee able to liue.</hi> Whereupon it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: that many runne on in the wide way of the world, that they may better compaſſe the wealth of the world.<note place="margin">Ioſ. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>Achan</hi> gaines his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly garment, his ſhekels of ſiluer, and wedge of gold, by <hi>ſtealth. Balaam</hi> would <hi>curſe</hi> to obtaine his wages. <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebell</hi> get the vineyard by <hi>murther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 21. Act. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Demetrius</hi> for his gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake doth raiſe an <hi>vproare</hi> againſt <hi>Paul. Demas,</hi> for his better aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage this way<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>forſaketh</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and embraceth the preſent world. And <hi>Iudas</hi> for the price of thirty pieces of ſiluer,<note place="margin">Mat 26.15.</note> 
               <hi>betraieth the Lord,</hi> his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>maſter.</hi> And to adde one more to increaſe the number. That Anti-chriſt of Rome, the pretended Vicar of Chriſt, but ſucceſſor of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> in his wicked practiſe, and ſonne &amp; heire of the Prince of this world, maketh marchandize of Gods word, of religion, of heauen, of hell, of the ſoules of men, of Chriſt, of God, and all; and all for the purchaſe of this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21501:61"/>gaine of the world. <hi>The loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the roote of all euill:</hi> the ſtep-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of goodneſſe: the mother of naughtineſſe: the mother-city of all iniquity. This thirſting deſire in the godleſſe worldling, that is may make way for richer returne, will expell and abandone naturall duty out of the familie, humane cruility out of the city, religion out of the Church, respect of good lawes out of the commonwealth, and all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and reſpect of iuſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, good and euill. It doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade many to violate friendſhip, to falſifie promiſe, to cozen their friends, to oppreſſe the poore, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the Orphanes, to murther the innocent, to ſpoile the Temple, to betray the country, blow vp the <hi>Parlament-houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Nou. 5. 1605.</note> to kill the Prince, to forſweare themſelues, to damne their ſoules, maliciouſly to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the God of Heauen: and, if it were poſſible to confound both heauen and earth, and to leaue no
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:21501:61"/>wickedneſſe vnattempted. Deſire of gold and gaine what doth it not conſtraine to vndertake? It is an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion as true as ancient: That, <hi>Ouer whomſoeuer couetouſneſſe hath domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hee is euidently ſubiect to all kinde of vices.</hi> And ſuch is the rode-way, wherein many a worldling doth ride, and runne, to leape, thereby, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faire houſes, large poſſeſſings, and places of account: ſometimes, it may bee, into the <hi>Emperours Throne;</hi> and very often into the <hi>Popes Chayre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what gaine is this?<note place="margin">Gen 25.33. Heb. 12.15.</note> to gaine the <hi>pottage,</hi> and to ſell the <hi>birth-right?</hi> to gaine the garment, and to looſe his faith? to gaine the ſiluer pieces, and to betray his Lord and Maſter? this is gaine in the coffer, but loſſe in the conſcience: gaine of the world, but loſſe of heauen. And ſuch is often the worldlings godleſſe gaine in getting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. In keeping.</note>Secondly; as the worldlings gaine expoſeth to daunger in getting: ſo
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:21501:62"/>it inwrappeth in danger in keeping. It intrappeth his minde, it winnes his affection, it inſnareth his heart, it bewitcheth his ſoule, it ſtealeth his loue and affection from God, and placeth and fixeth them vpon it ſelfe, and cauſeth him, oft-times, not onely, moſt vniuſtly to defraud both himſelfe and others of the vſe of it, but impiouſly and ſuperſtitiouſly to honour it as a God: to place his affiance &amp; confidence therein, &amp; to turne baſe-ſlaue to <hi>Mammon</hi> his Lord and his God. The ambitious worldling is in the ſame caſe: for al-beit the people ſerue him, yet his ambitious deſire to dominere ouer others, doth moſt imperiouſly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minere ouer him. Hee adores ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authority; as his Prince and God: ſo his glory is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhame. The voluptuous world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> who drownes himſelfe in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, yeelds himſelfe captiue to his imperious Dames, turnes ſlaue to his luſte,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> and makes his <hi>belly his God,</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:21501:62"/>and purchaſeth to himſelfe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the end, and ſuch is often the worldlings gaine in keeping.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 In ſpending</note>Thirdly; the worldlings gaine expoſeth him to daunger in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; while it draweth from humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to pride; from ſobriety to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot: from moderation to exceſſe: from labour to voluptuouſneſſe: from chaſtity to vncleanneſſe: from loue and practiſe of vertue and piety, to liking and following of iniquity and vice.</p>
            <p>Oh how many and great are the daungers and difficulties which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this gaine of the world in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and in keeping, and in ſpending the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cum itſis opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus laſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uire coepit Eccleſia. Platina in Bened. IIII.</note>The Church of God had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hereof, which, when it waxed wealthy, beganne to waxe wanton, and it was not cauſeleſly obſerued by one of the Auncient; That,<note place="margin">Religto pep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it diuitia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; filia denorauit matrem. Aug.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion brought forth wealth and the daughter deuoured the mother, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Church of God, (God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21501:63"/>knoweth) who haue ſtood in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, haue fallen in proſperity: haue increaſed in goodneſſe while the world frowned, but decreaſed in grace when the world fawned. The world by fawning deceiueth, and by embracing killeth; and bleſſed is hee that hath both worldly wealth and heauenly wiſdome,</p>
            <p>And ſo euery way dangerous is this gaine of the world, while it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnareth with deſire of getting: op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth with care of keeping: cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth with voluptuouſneſſe in ſpending.</p>
            <p>Who therefore can eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, theſe goods, which are gotten ſo badly? or this wealth which is kept ſo woefully? or this gaine, which is ſpent ſo hurtfully? and what great gaine is this of the world, that brings in daunger of the loſſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The gaine of godlineſſe is free from daunger. 1. In getting.</note>There is no ſuch danger in the gaine of godlineſſe. It is not got but by good and godly means: through
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:21501:63"/>the ordinances of God, and worke of Gods ſpirit. No ill meanes can be an immediate cauſe of any ſpirituall good: but if any euill be occaſion of any ſuch good, it's by the skilfull hand of Gods omnipotent goodnes, that turnes poiſon into potions, and euill to good.<note place="margin">2. In Keeping.</note> This gaine is not kept but in good and godly manner, not layd vp in a napkin, but put out to Gods vſe. It is not beſtowed, but to good and godly purpoſes.<note place="margin">3. In beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> And it doth not only make the owner ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of good through getting, better through keeping, and beſt of all by vſing it well; but it doth teach and direct to vſe the worlds gaine well which without this wee could not but vſe very ill:<note place="margin">Godlineſſe teacheth how to vſe worldly gaine well.</note> and that while it wel aduiſeth, not to place our happineſſe in it, but to further our happineſſe by wiſe employment of it: by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>friends of this vnrighteous Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> that wee <hi>may bee receiued into that euerlaſting habitation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 16.9.</note> And when this gaine of godlines hath brought
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:21501:64"/>vs to our beſt condition heere, it will put vs into poſſeſſion of perfection elſewhere: and that not in this earth below, where this worldly gaine is got, and vſed, and left behinde vs: but in heauen aboue, whence this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, where it is reſerued: &amp; where it ſhall be moſt happily enioyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings gaine cannot make happy: this of godlines can.</note>Laſtly, that I may not bee infinite in this diſcourſe, but may come to a concluſion of this compariſon. That gaine of the world makes many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, none happy: this of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes all happy, none miſerable. Thoſe goods,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſuch men may haue as are not good, and therefore not happy. Theſe, none but ſuch as are good and therfore not miſerable. That world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wealth makes neither vs nor our children happy: for either while we liue, wee looſe it: or when wee die, wee leaue it, to whom wee know not, or to whom we would not. But this is ſuch as neither leaues vs, nor we it: but remayneth euer with vs, euer to enrich vs. And whereas hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21501:64"/>is not enioyed but in fruition of God, who is the onely felicity of the ſoule of man. This gaine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe vniteth vs to God, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our <hi>bleſſedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.15.</note> while the <hi>Lord is our God.</hi> And that not onely in this couenant of grace: but ſpecially in that communion of glory,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.2 3.</note> with God in Chriſt; which is the fulneſſe and vp-ſhot of all felicitie,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.19.</note> where God filleth all in all: and where wee ſhall be filled with all fulneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>Now to apply all this vnto our ſelues. The Merchants of whom I ſpeak, are (among the reſt, you, Right Honourable and beloued) vnto whom I ſpeake. The gaine at which I would aduiſe you to aime, is the purchaſe of Godlineſſe, That true, that great, that al-ſufficient gaine. Your talents and meanes of purchaſe are, your abilities of body, minde, eſtate, ioyned with the holy and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ordinances of God. Your tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke and trading is your manner of cariage, in your purpoſes, deſires, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:21501:65"/>ſtudies and endeauours both of heart and life. The Mart-day is at hand, the day of grace is come, the the Sunne is vp, the Goſpell is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. Theſe precious wares of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe are readily expoſed to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen view of all willing beholders, all wiſe and prouident merchants, all prudent profeſſours, are buſie at their worke, and redeeme fore-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time by double diligence in their painefull endeauour. The owner of all this wealth doth cal vnto you, by the miniſtery of his ſeruants, in the preaching of his word, ſaying. What lacke you? what buy you? Come: ſee: buy: gaine: be happy, be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Come; purchaſe the <hi>hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> this <hi>goodly pearle:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.44.76.45.</note> The prizeleſſe wealth: this wel-contenting gaine of pietie and Godlineſſe. Come now while the day laſteth, God knoweth how ſoone our ſunne may ſet. Come all, young, ould, rich, poore, learned, vnlearned, meane, great. None tis too good, too great, too meane, too
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:21501:65"/>miſerable, to trade in this merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>King</hi> himſelfe account it the crowne of his glory,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to bee firſt of this company: as it is his deſerued honour to bee chiefe of all the reſt. And let him more feelingly reioyce: with good <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to bee a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church,<note place="margin">Se eſſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum eccleſiae magis quam in terris regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Aug. de ciuit. Dei lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> then a Monarch in the world: to be truly ſtiled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Defender of one true faith,</hi> then to be rightfull Ruler of three larg King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Let him make choice with King <hi>Dauid, rather to bee a doore-keeper in the Houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> 
               <hi>then to rule &amp; raigne in the tabernacles of vngodlineſſe.</hi> Much more to bee <hi>keeper</hi> of both the <hi>Tables</hi> of Gods law: a <hi>Prince</hi> and feeder of the people of God: and by lawes and authoritie, by learning and induſtry; in heart, by hand,<note place="margin">Pietas eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Imperatoris ornatus. Euagr. hiſt praefat. 2d Theodoſium (iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorem) imperae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem.</note> a reſolute <hi>Patrone</hi> and bright ſhining <hi>patterne,</hi> of (this chiefe ornament of an Emperour) religion and <hi>godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Queene</hi> his happy yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow ioyne heart and hand in this,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:21501:66"/>and become a bleſſed helpe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their mutuall bleſſedneſſe. Let her make it appeare with the <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Sheba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 10.</note> that her chiefe end of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from farre, was to heare this true wiſdome from the mouth of her <hi>Salomon.</hi> Let her try him with que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and receiue his anſwers; and account her ſelfe happy to be partner with him, in this wiſdome and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of pietie and <hi>godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the moſt hopefull <hi>Prince,</hi> in the morning of his ſtate, lay the ground &amp; foundation of his prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greatneſſe, in the deſired returne of theſe rich reuenues. Let him eſteeme this gaine of <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> the chiefe part of his <hi>patrimonie,</hi> and his hopes in <hi>heauen</hi> his happieſt <hi>inheritance,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Ho. Lords and <hi>Counſellors</hi> of ſtate, who aduiſe for the weale and wel-fare of this land, conſult for the enriching of this renowmed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with a bleſſed increaſe in this gaine of <hi>godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the noble Lords and <hi>Peeres</hi> of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:21501:66"/>the land, innoble their bloud in the bloud of Chriſt: enrich their eſtates with his treaſures of grace: and place their felicity in the fauour of God. Let goodneſſe be their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and religion their renowne, and this gaine of godlineſſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>And you right Honourable the Lord Maior, with other the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and all the inhabitants of this famous City, giue me leaue to ſpeake vnto you. You trade by your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: you gaine by your trading: and you riſe by your gaine vnto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect. Gods bleſſing be vpon you, in your outward eſtates; and bleſſe your trafique with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable increaſe: and giue you your hearts deſire, ſo your hearts be vpright. But take heede to your ſelues, I pray you, that you goe not downe the winde. Leaue of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (I beſeech you, from the Lord) thoſe hurtfull courſes, incident to your places,<note place="margin">Mich. 6.10.11.12.</note> of worthleſſe profits
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:21501:67"/>too too much vſed by too many of your company. Their corrupting of wares, ingroſſing of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, inhaunſing of prices, falſhood and deceit, in buying, and ſelling, weight, meaſure, and the like. Leſt you finde gaine in the cheſt, but loſſe in the conſcience: increaſe of goods, but decreaſe of goodneſſe: proue rich in the world,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.21.</note> but <hi>not in God.</hi> Oh, purchaſe pietie, gaine god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, grow rich in grace: ſo ſhall your hearts and liues bee holy, your eſtates wealthy, and your perſons happy in the day of your great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
            <p>You <hi>reuerend Iudges,</hi> and Miniſters of iuſtice, bee louers of iuſtice, and not of <hi>reward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 3.9.11.</note> Suffer not your eyes to be blinded with bribes, and your hearts to bee corrupted with gifts in your boſome, to make you <hi>wreſt iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17.23.</note> and <hi>peruert the right.</hi> Oh iudge you right for the <hi>fatherleſſe and widowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 1.17.</note> though your ſentence and pleading ſhould paſſe both
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:21501:67"/>without gift, and gaine: ſo ſhal you waxe rich in this gaine of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: your cauſe ſhall goe well at the great aſſiſes: and you ſhall eſcape the dreadfull ſentence of the higheſt Iudge of all.</p>
            <p>You <hi>Patrones</hi> and beſtowers of the reuenewes of the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecirated to their vſe, who ſerue at Gods Altar, no more enrich your ſelues with the price of blood: while, by bargaine and ſale, you paſſe them ouer,<note place="margin">Eſa. 56.10.11.</note> into the hands of <hi>vnable and vnconſcionable</hi> men. Who through negligence in teaching, or bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of lewde life, doe little leſſe then murther the ſoules of the poore people of God. Oh make wiſe choyce (I beſeech you) of men of deſert, for learning and life, fit to bee paſtors of ſoules: ſo ſhall you gaine comfort to your ſelues, and good to Gods Church, through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of godlineſſe, and religion of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You <hi>Land-lords,</hi> and letters of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:21501:68"/>of tenements and grounds, in no wiſe oppreſſe, and <hi>grind the faces of the poore;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 3.15.</note> by racking and exacting aboue due meaſure, or ouer-charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with burdens too heauy to bee borne. Oh deale in loue, deale in pittie, with your poore Chriſtian brethren, that they may not (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtreſſed ones doe) droope and languiſh with griefe and ſorrow, but may ioyne with you in cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the ſeruice of God: ſo ſhall you both grow rich in this gaine of godlineſſe, and find a better increaſe in this heauenly wealth.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>poore,</hi> whoſe eſtate is weake in the world, amend his condition by this gainefull purchaſe of grace into his heart: that this ſpirituall wealth may ſupply his wants, and the riches of Chriſt may releeue his miſery.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.</note> Let the poore <hi>labourer</hi> toile all the day of his painefull life, that hee may receiue this peny at the night of his death. Let no time ſeeme long, no trauell tedious. This
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:21501:68"/>peny will bring him true felicity, and make vp his want of that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den droſſe, which worldlings ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire in this preſent life.</p>
            <p>And whom ſhould I further name? Let byting <hi>vſurers,</hi> become free lenders. Let blood-ſucking <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners</hi> become ready reſtorers.<note place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> Let poore-murthering <hi>oppreſſors</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come comfortable helpers. Let pinching <hi>miſers</hi> become bountifull benefactors. And all of vs good to our brethren, in conſcience vnto God: that all may attaine this gaine of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Let the high Lords <hi>Treaſurers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1. Mat. 13.52.</note> the <hi>Seruants</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>learned ſcribes,</hi> and faithfull <hi>ſtewards</hi> of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.2.</note> bring out of the Scriptures, the Treaſuries of the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7.</note> the true <hi>treaſure</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the ſoules of the people of God. Though <hi>gold and ſiluer wee haue none, yet ſuch as wee haue,</hi> let vs <hi>giue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.10. 2. Cor. 6.10.</note> ſo wee being <hi>poore,</hi> ſhall <hi>make many rich:</hi> and grow rich our ſelues, by enriching our brethren. While we are liberall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:21501:69"/>to others, God will be bountifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and multiply our talents vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our hands.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let all that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, ioyne ſtocke, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come partners in this happy gaine. or if the fooliſh and vnhappy world, will needs graſpe at the ſhadowes of tranſitory gaine, and will needes grow wealthy, by falſhood and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, bribery and extortion, and all kinde of vniuſtice, and vnderhand dealing: Eating the bread of deceit, taking the wages of iniquity, and expecting rewards with vnhappy <hi>Felix.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.26.</note> Yet thou, O man of God, O godly man, haue thou nothing to doe with that vnrighteous <hi>Mammon.</hi> But partake with other godly in the happy intereſt, of theſe ſubſtantiall, and eternall treaſures.</p>
            <p>And what if the <hi>godleſſe</hi> man goe away with the gaine of the world? Looke not thou on his wealth with an enuious eye, nor on his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with an vnquiet ſpirit. It is
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:21501:69"/>weakeneſſe of ſpirit to bee diſquieted with variety of deſire after the worlds gaine, for thy ſelfe; or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy at the fruition thereof, in others. Thou art a Chriſtian indeed, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gainer then the world can make thee: and a ſurer keeper, then that the world can hurt thee. As for him, he is miſerable, to be pittied, not happy to be enuied: thou art hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to bee enuied: and withall, ſo happy, as not to bee hurt by enuy. Let not the conceit of his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty moleſt thee: but the aſſurance of thine owne felicity content thee. As thou ſhouldeſt not reioyce at his ſoules loſſe: ſo ſhouldſt thou not be grieued at his worlds gaine. He is a broken-ſtated bankrupt, that takes vp for day, and receiues a penny to returne a pound: thou art a rich heir, who liueſt on thy ſmall penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the time of thy minority; thine inheritance is reſerued for thee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, till thou come to age.</p>
            <p>And what, if for this ſpirituall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:21501:70"/>gaine, thou bee faine to ſit downe with ſome temporall loſſe? better it is to begge thy bread then to looſe thy faith. Better to caſt ouer-boord ſome parcell of thy goods, then to make ſhip-wracke of thy good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Neither ſhall this proue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loſſe at all, but an happy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for thy better aduantage; of wealth, of delights, and honour on earth; for riches, and pleaſures, and glory in heauen. And thus did thoſe <hi>godly</hi> ones of old <hi>ſolace</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their light loſſes with hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expectation of greater gaine:<note place="margin">Sic magnis ſunt lucris leuta d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſolati. Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more enduring ſubſtance.</hi> They <hi>eſteemed with Moſes the rebukes of Chriſt greater riches then the treaſures of Egypt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr 10.34. Hebr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.26.</note> and could not be with-drawen,<note place="margin">Nul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o praemio huius mundi ab aeternae illiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> patriae ſocietat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeducti. Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> by any wordly reward, from the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that heauenly country. <hi>They had reſpect to the recompenſe of reward,</hi> which was the rich returne of this gaine of godlineſſe:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> a ſure increaſe of a ful <hi>hundreth-fold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 19.29.</note> with a promiſed inheritance of <hi>euerlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:21501:70"/>
Come therefore now, whoſoeuer thou art, that beareſt the name and ſhew of a Chriſtian: dote no longer vpon theſe worldly vanities. Reſt not bewitched with the pleaſing ſhew, or ſmell, or ſound of worldly gaine. And if thou haſt heretofore either immoderately deſired, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully obtained that copper-met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, guilt ouer to beguile thee: leaue off betimes that hurtfull trade. Turne thy ſelfe forth-with vnto a better courſe. Take heed and beware (in the name of God) of godleſſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, of wicked worldlineſſe, of graceleſſe voluptuouſneſſe, and profane lewdneſſe; with all thoſe open practiſes of cruelty, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice; and ſecret myſteries of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iniquities. Thoſe ſworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of religion: thoſe cut-throates of goodneſſe: thoſe deuiliſh hauock-makers of the <hi>gaine of godlineſſe:</hi> and deſperate ouer-turners of thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good eſtate</p>
            <p>Deſire new profits, ſeeke for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:21501:71"/>gaines. <hi>Firſt ſeeke the Kingdome of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>and his righteouſneſſe.</hi> Firſt in time before all: firſt in degree aboue all other gaine. Yea, firſt, and laſt, and without interruption, euen in the middeſt of thy earthly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And giue all diligence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. For howſoeuer the world flowes in on many, of it owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: yet this gaine comes not in without good indeauour. <hi>God</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is free and ready to giue it: but none that are careleſſe are fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it;<note place="margin">Prou. 2.4.</note> but muſt <hi>digge</hi> and delue, and blow and ſweate, if they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelues with theſe hidden treaſures.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.44.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Well then; doeſt thou, from thy very heart, deſire thine owne true weale and wel-fare? which if thou doe not, oh fooliſh man thou, and moſt miſerable! but doeſt thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from thy ſoule deſire it? then vſe, I beſeech thee, all thy will and skill, all thy induſtrie and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in timely proſecution of ſuch
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:21501:71"/>holy endeauours, as God himſelfe hath made the happy meanes of this moſt bleſſed gaine.</p>
            <p>Be inſtant in reading, hearing, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating and conferring of the holy Word of God, be frequent in earneſt inuocation of the holy name of God. Exerciſe thy ſelfe inceſſantly in the duties of repentance, and new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Labour for faith, for hope, for loue, and feare of God, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſanctifying and ſauing graces, as for life it ſelfe, euen the life of thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>Let ſlippe no time, no occaſion, no helpes of daily increaſe &amp; growth in this heauenly wealth: let the word of God dwell in thee <hi>richly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Col. 3.16.</note> through ſacred and ſauing knowledge. Let thoſe bleſſed rich graces of Gods ſanctifying ſpirit bee treaſured vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly, in the ſtore-houſe of thy ſoule. Repleniſh both heart, and minde, memorie, and conſcience, &amp; euery roome, and corner of thy ſoule. And when thou haſt gotten
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:21501:72"/>aboundantly, <hi>keepe</hi> it ſafely, that ſo thou mayeſt both liue and die rich &amp; wealthy,<note place="margin">Prou. 4.23.</note> in this gaine of godlineſſe: and being rich in grace mayeſt bee rich in glory.</p>
            <p>And if thou ſhalt in this holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner demeane thy ſelfe, and through faithfull employment of thy ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all talents, ſhalt giue account to thy Lord of a good increaſe. Then ſhalt thou hear with thy eare, to the ioy of thy heart:<note place="margin">Mat. 25.21.23.</note> 
               <hi>Well done thou good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant, thou haſt beene faithfull ouer a few things, I will make thee ruler ouer many things: enter thou into the ioy of thy Lord:</hi> Thou haſt beene faithfull, as a <hi>ſeruant:</hi> I will make thee a <hi>Ruler.</hi> Thou haſt beene faithfull ouer a <hi>few</hi> things; I will make thee ruler ouer <hi>many</hi> things. Thou haſt beene faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the imployment of thy maſters <hi>talents:</hi> enter now into the <hi>ioy of thy Lord.</hi> And what is this ioy? ſurely, the bleſſed fruition of thy Lord and Sauiour, in communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of thy Father, and Holy ſpirit.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21501:72"/>Where thou ſhalt enioy, euen ioy without ſorrow: welth without wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: honour, without diſgrace: pleaſure without paine: peace without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe: light without darkneſſe: health without ſickenes: life with out death: This <hi>wel-contenting gaine of pietie and godlineſſe:</hi> that eternall frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of felicity and bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now bleſſed Lord God, thou God of all grace, rich in grace, in mercy, and bounty, to all that feare and call vpon thee. Vouchſafe, we moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee, to make all grace to abound vnto vs all: that wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hauing al-ſufficiency in all good things, may abound to euery good worke. Enrich our hearts with the treaſures of godlineſſe: ſettle our affections with godly contentment: and grant vnto vs a dayly increaſe in this trueſt and richeſt gaine; that we may comfortably enioy all needefull bleſſings in this life, and full fruition of glory and felicity in the life to come. And that through the al-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:21501:73"/>merits of thine onely Sonne, and our alone Sauiour, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, to whom with thee, O father, and thy bleſſed ſpirit, one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe and al-ſufficient God, bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed of vs, &amp; of thy whole Church, all honour, glory, praiſe, power, dominion, and thankſgiuing, from this time forth for euermore: Amen.</p>
            <trailer>All glorie be to God.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21501:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
